<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Augustus. Or, An essay of those meanes and counsels, whereby the commonwealth of Rome was altered, and reduced unto a monarchy</title>
            <author>Heylyn, Peter, 1600-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 120 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14007</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839753_4203</idno>
  <idno type="VID">4203</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248565788</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 13268</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S104012</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99839753e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14007)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4203)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 650:3, 1070:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Augustus. Or, An essay of those meanes and counsels, whereby the commonwealth of Rome was altered, and reduced unto a monarchy</title>
                  <author>Heylyn, Peter, 1600-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 135, 134-227, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B[ernard] A[lsop] and T[homas] F[awcet] for Henry Seile at the Tygers head in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Peter Heylyn.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 957 on UMI microfilm reel 650.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in Cambridge University Library and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 650 (Cambridge University Library copy) and at reel 1070 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Augustus, --  Emperor of Rome, 63 B.C.-14 A.D. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Rome --  History --  Republic, 265-30 B.C. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4203:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4203:1"/>
            <p>AVGVSTVS. OR, <hi>An Essay of those</hi> Meanes and Counsels, whereby the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> of ROME was altered, and reduced unto a <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(∵)</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>VIRG. Aeneid. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Tu regere imperio Populos</l>
               <l>Romane memento:</l>
               <l>Hae tibi erunt artes.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>B. A.</hi> and <hi>T. F.</hi> for <hi>Henry Scile</hi> at the <hi>Tygers</hi> head in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4203:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4203:2"/>
            <head>TO MY MVCH HONORED FRIEND, THOMAS LEVET of <hi>Ticksore,</hi> in the County of <hi>Rutland,</hi> Esquire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Essay,</hi> long since written by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor for his private
<pb facs="tcp:4203:3"/> satisfaction, is now by his consent made common, &amp; for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in it, a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the greatest change, that ever happened in the Common-wealth and state of <hi>Rome.</hi> Yet not a naked Story nor a bare Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion onely; but a
<pb facs="tcp:4203:3"/> briefe touch of all such Counsailes, and arts of Empire, by the meanes whereof it was effected; Such as could either be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of those times, or gathered vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny probable conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, or grounds of State. In which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is so farre from ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4203:4"/> of satisfying others, that as yet hee hath not satisfied himself, and cannot but bee sensible, that he hath drawne this Picture of <hi>AVGVSTVS</hi> with too much shadow. Such as it is, I conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate to you, and to your perusall.</p>
            <p>The many obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which you haue
<pb facs="tcp:4203:4"/> vpon the Author, may make just chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge for you vnto any thing of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. Were it not so, that liberall Humanitie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you have vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed for his sake, to reflect on mee, is of it selfe suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to embolden mee to this presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:4203:5"/> and to subscribe my selfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your obliged Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, HENRY SEILE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4203:5"/>
            <head>AVGVSTVS. OR, AN ESSAY OF THOSE MEANES and Counsailes, by which the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of ROME was altered and reduced unto a <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HEY which have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore written of <hi>Common-wealths,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:4203:6"/> have divided them into three Species: The government of the <hi>King;</hi> secondly, of the <hi>Nobles;</hi> and thirdly of the <hi>People.</hi> Ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of these is againe subdivided into <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evill:</hi> The <hi>evill</hi> forme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely the <hi>good</hi> corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; The <hi>good</hi> nothing else, but the <hi>bad</hi> refined. So is the government of a <hi>King,</hi> divided into a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and a <hi>Tyranny:</hi> Of the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> into an <hi>Aristocracy,</hi> and an <hi>Oligarchy:</hi> Of the <hi>People</hi> into a <hi>Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke,</hi> and a <hi>Democracy.</hi> All these, as well in generall, as in the several couplets, have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4203:6"/> a secret Inclination to change the one <hi>into</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to make a <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goricall</hi> transmigration (as it were) into each others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. I need not stand on ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny instances. The Cōmon-wealth of <hi>Rome</hi> (into whose stories whosoever loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, will judge them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to containe the acts of the whole World, then a particular Nation) will serve for all. ROMVLVS at the foundation of his Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, reserved unto himselfe the chiefe Soveraignty, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it entire to his succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors. NVMA, ANCVS, TVLLIVS, TARQVINIVS
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4203:7"/> PRISCVS, and SERVIVS, governed themselves so moderately, the people so justly: that they affected not <hi>Tyranny;</hi> nor the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons liberty. They ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared more desirous to fill the <hi>Coffers</hi> of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, then their owne <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suries:</hi> And when necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty compelled them to a Taxe; they rather seemed to sheere their sheepe, then fleece them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>BVt SVPERBVS, a man of insupportable vices, having by violence enthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized himselfe in that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4203:7"/> Chayre of State, which had not his ambitious spirit beene impatient of delay, would have beene his rightfull Inheritance; made his gouernment an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to his entrance, cruell and bloudy. How many men, eminent as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well by their owne ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as their Parents No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, did hee cut off? How many did he for no cause promote, to make their fall the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable? What part of the <hi>Senate</hi> was free from slaughter? What corner of the City from lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations? Yet this was not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4203:8"/> all. The miserable <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> were visited with Three plagues at once. <hi>Pride</hi> in the Father, <hi>Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in the Mother, and <hi>Lust</hi> insatiable in their sonne SEXTVS; a true <hi>Copie</hi> of the old <hi>Originals.</hi> Either of these had beene more then enough, to exercise the peoples patience. But meeting all at one time, it seemed that nothing could now bee added to the wretchednesse of the one, and the wickednesse of the other. BRVTVS, a man fatall to Tyrants, did easily perswade the <hi>Commons</hi> to shake off this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4203:8"/> yoake. For they, aswell desirous of <hi>Novelties,</hi> as sensible of <hi>Oppressions,</hi> had long since murmured at the present State; and wanted nothing but a head, to breake into actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all rebellion. So the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> got the <hi>freedome,</hi> and the <hi>Kings</hi> lost the <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> of the City. (<hi>An. V C.</hi> 244.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>BRVTVS although hee wanted no faire title to the <hi>Crowne;</hi> yet eyther perceiuing how odious the name of <hi>King</hi> was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4203:9"/> growne; or perhaps wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be rather the first <hi>Consull,</hi> then the last <hi>Prince;</hi> instituted a new forme of Government. Wherein the sway of all, was referred to the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> of the <hi>City:</hi> Out of whom two were annually chosen as chiefe of the rest. Herein certainly hee dealt very advisedly, For had he sought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme himselfe in the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> what could men judge, but that, not love to his Country was the cause that stirred him to take Armes; but desire of Rule. Againe, besides
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4203:9"/> that secure <hi>privacie,</hi> is to bee preferred before ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous <hi>Royaltie;</hi> what hope had hee to keepe the seate long, having by his owne example taught the people, both the <hi>Theorie</hi> and <hi>practise</hi> of <hi>Rebellion.</hi> Vnder this new <hi>Aristocracy</hi> the <hi>Romā</hi> affaires succeeded so prosperously, their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions were inlarged so infinitly: that it may well bee questioned; whether the <hi>Roman</hi> fortune caused their greatnes; or their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour cōmanded their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. For the Governors not seeking wealth but honour, or not their owne
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4203:10"/> wealth but the publike; did so demean themselves both in peace and warre: that there was betweene all, a vertuous emulation; who should most benefit his Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>THis happinesse was too great to continue long. The people had as yet no written <hi>Statutes: Custome</hi> bearing most sway; and the rest of the <hi>Law,</hi> locked up in the breast of the <hi>Iudges.</hi> To avoid such inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as might hence ensue,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4203:10"/> there were some men, knowne to be as sound in judgement, as honest in their actions, deputed by a generall Commission to take an abstract of the <hi>Graecian lawes:</hi> according to the tenor whereof, the <hi>people</hi> framed their <hi>lives;</hi> the <hi>Iudges,</hi> their <hi>sentences.</hi> Here followed the <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchy</hi> or <hi>Decemvirate State</hi> of <hi>Rome; (An. V C.</hi> 304.) but long it lasted not. For these new <hi>Lords</hi> joyning forces together, made themselves rich with the spoyle of the <hi>people:</hi> not caring by what unlawfull meanes, they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4203:11"/> could purchase either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or pleasure. APPIVS CLAVDIVS, one of the <hi>Decemviri,</hi> was the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neck of this government. Hee, unmindfull of LV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRETIA and the <hi>Tarquins,</hi> lusted after VIRGINIA; a woman though of lowe Condition, yet such a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in whom beauty and vertue strove for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminencie. She was, in an open assembly to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the dishonor of his child, slaine by her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: APPIVS forced to make away himselfe, in prison; and the rest of that <hi>Magistracie</hi> abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4203:11"/> their Offices, the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suls</hi> were for a time resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>People</hi> fleshed with this victory, &amp; calling to minde how their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors had in like manner banished the <hi>Kings;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to know their owne strength: and stomacked it exceedingly, that they on whose shoulders the frame of the State was supported, should bee so much under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of others; that they who were <hi>Lords</hi> abroad,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4203:12"/> should be below the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Slaves</hi> at home. Hereupon they raise a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult, under the conduct of their <hi>Tribune,</hi> CANV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEIVS. Nor could they by any perswasions bee induced to lay downe Armes, till they had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a <hi>Decree,</hi> That from thenceforth, the <hi>Nobles</hi> and the <hi>Commons,</hi> might promiscuously bee marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And this was the first step to the <hi>Republique. (An. V C.</hi> 308.) The gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this new <hi>Priviledge,</hi> put them in possibility of obtaining greater. They now sue to bee capable of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4203:12"/> the <hi>Consulship.</hi> The <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> consulting of this demand, wisely fore-saw, that to grant their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to deny it was alike dangerous. For were it utterly dashed, it was to bee feared the <hi>People</hi> would againe forsake the <hi>Citty;</hi> and yet make their stay more insolent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>supportable, if it were granted. <hi>C. Claudius,</hi> one who by his honourable behaviour, was by both parties had in an equall degree of Reverence; quickly proposed a mid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dle course; whereby the fury of the multitude
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4203:13"/> might be appeased, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blemish to the <hi>Consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> dignity. He constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 6. Annuall Officers, equally chosen out of the <hi>People,</hi> and the <hi>Nobles:</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them <hi>Tribuni Militū Cōsularis potestatis. (A. V. C.</hi> 310). This Office continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but not without many <hi>Interstitiúms,</hi> the space of 78. yeares. Which time expired, and some expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience being had of the peoples government; the <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Senate</hi> did decree, that one of the <hi>Consuls</hi> should frō thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth be chosen by, and out of the <hi>Commons;</hi> that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4203:13"/> they should be capable of all <hi>Magistracies;</hi> yea even of the <hi>Dictatorship. (An. V. C.</hi> 388.) So that now vertue was as speedy a Ladder, to climbe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Honours, as <hi>Nobility of Birth:</hi> and a <hi>good man</hi> as much respected as a <hi>great.</hi> A rare felicity of the times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>People</hi> being thus mixt with the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> as well in marriages, as honours; one would
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4203:14"/> have thought that this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> being thus equally poysed had been immortall. But as in the <hi>naturall body,</hi> there can be no exact and <hi>arithmeticall</hi> proportion of the humors and elements, without some <hi>predominancie:</hi> So in the <hi>body politique,</hi> can there bee no equall mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Plebeians</hi> and <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> without the supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of the one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The <hi>people</hi> had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently after the institution of the <hi>Consuls,</hi> raysed a Commotion; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew themselves into <hi>Mount Aventine.</hi> Nor
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4203:14"/> could they bee intreated to returne into the <hi>Citty,</hi> till there were granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them peculiar <hi>Officers,</hi> called <hi>Tribuni Plebis,</hi> or Protectors of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. (<hi>A. V. C.</hi> 260.) These being not long after by the common Councell, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to bee <hi>Sacrosan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti,</hi> and inviolable; began to heave the <hi>Popular State</hi> too high, and thrust the <hi>Aristocraticall</hi> too low; not regarding to lose the love of the one, so they might get the applause of the other. Insomuch, that matters of judgement
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4203:15"/> were devolved from the <hi>Fathers</hi> to the <hi>Commons;</hi> and the authority of the <hi>Senate,</hi> trode under foote by the <hi>People.</hi> Nay they proceeded so farre, That MARIVS being <hi>Tribune,</hi> threatned to send COTTA the <hi>Consull</hi> unto Prison. And SVLPITIVS in the same <hi>Office,</hi> made the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suls</hi> forsake the <hi>Senate-house:</hi> and slew one of their sonnes, whose heeles were not nimble enough, to flye away. And now were the <hi>Romans</hi> gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by that forme of <hi>Rule,</hi> than which there is no lower. So that as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4203:15"/> well by an inevitable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity in <hi>Nature,</hi> as the ordinary course of <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies;</hi> there must be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession to the first, and <hi>Monarchicall</hi> Iurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For questionlesse it fareth many times with a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as with the <hi>Sunne:</hi> which runneth through all the signes of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> till it return to the place where its moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on first began. And the <hi>Platonicke</hi> yeare of redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all things to the same beginning, continuance, and period; how false so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in the bookes of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> is in some sort true
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4203:16"/> in the change of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>THe way downe-Hill is easie and ordinary but to ascend unto the top requireth both wit to frame steps, &amp; courage to give the attempt. So was it here also w<seg rend="sup">th</seg> the <hi>Romās.</hi> They had naturally, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most insensibly falne from a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> to a <hi>Populacy,</hi> or <hi>Democracy.</hi> But to ascēd frō a <hi>Populacy</hi> to a <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> required many steps &amp; degrees in many, much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4203:16"/> in al. <hi>Marius</hi> &amp; <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> well skilled in feeding the humors of the <hi>people,</hi> were the first that attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; severally mounted to such a height of <hi>Cōmād;</hi> as never durst any promise to thē, nor they hope for themselves. <hi>Marius</hi> was of an harsh &amp; sterne nature, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually cruel to the <hi>enemies</hi> in war, &amp; the <hi>people</hi> in <hi>peace:</hi> one whose birth the <hi>Rom.</hi> might have had just cause to curse, had hee not saved thē from the <hi>Cimbri. Sylla</hi> was one whose cariage none could enogh cōmēd before, or sufficiently cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn after his prosperity.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4203:17"/> A man, whose <hi>Peace</hi> was farre more bloudy than his <hi>Warres;</hi> a better <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,</hi> than a <hi>Prince.</hi> These two gave way each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and both to death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>NExt these, as wel in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and designes, as bloud and alliance, succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded CAESAR and POM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PEY: Two men never tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paraleld, since their owne times. CAESAR had a wit to invent so preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, a heart to execute
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4203:17"/> so stout, and to both a Fortune so favourable; that hee durst undertake what no man dared, and his performances com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly were answerable to his undertakings. POM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PEY, a man greater than his owne or his friends wishes; had triumphed over all the parts of the knowne world: and could hee but have brooked an equall, hee had never met superiour. Had these two lived in divers Ages, or exercised their valour on the common Enemy; the world had beene too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to yeeld them imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4203:18"/> But turning their forces one against the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, POMPEY over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne in the <hi>Field,</hi> was basely murthered in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt:</hi> and CAESAR victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously Conquerour in <hi>Thessalie,</hi> was barbarous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly massacred in the <hi>Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll.</hi> And though none of these foure Worthies, could settle the <hi>Monarchie</hi> in himselfe; yet this shall bee to their eternall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory recorded, that they first opened the passage to others, and first mooved the stone, which rowling along tumbled the <hi>People</hi> out of the <hi>Government.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:4203:18"/>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>AFter the overthrow of POMPEY, &amp; death of CAESAR, the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> might have reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>Liberty,</hi> if either CAESAR had left no heire, and POMPEY no Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: or rather if ANTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIVS, a man of an unquiet and turbulent spirit, had not begun new troubles. For hee, knowing the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the <hi>Common people</hi> unto young OC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAVIVS, CAESARS heire:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4203:19"/> and hearing the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all report of his approach to <hi>Rome</hi> for his Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; did by <hi>Decree</hi> of <hi>Senate</hi> restore SEXTVS the sonne of POMPEY to his blood and honours. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that they two, inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting their Fathers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treds, would like Pellets in a Boyes Pot-gun, drive out each other; and so he might remaine <hi>Lord</hi> of the whole. But young OCTAVIVS, was too old to be so fetcht over: and had moreover more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to revenge his Fathers death on BRVTVS and CASSIVS, than turne
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4203:19"/> himselfe upon an enemy, that neither had done, nor could doe him any hurt. At his first entry into <hi>Rome,</hi> hee declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe CAESARS heire; though some regarding more his welfare than his honour, disswaded him from it. His retinue at his entrance was but small, his behaviour gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and courteous: So that all had cause to love him, none to feare him. His first businesse was to ANTONIVS, then posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of all CAESARS estate. His words as modest, as his Petition just. ANTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIES
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4203:20"/> answere somewhat churlish, forbidding him to meddle in matters of <hi>State,</hi> that hee was too young to take upon him the <hi>Name</hi> of CAESAR, and so dismissed him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satisfied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>AVGVSTVS (for by that name wee meane to call him, though hee was not yet so called) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that ANTHONIES answer, though in shew but a <hi>Delay,</hi> was in effect
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4203:20"/> a <hi>Deniall:</hi> insinuated into the acquaintance of CI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERO, then potent among the Senators, and a capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Enemy of ANTHONY; by meanes whereof the <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Senate,</hi> began to cast great affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him. Next in a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Oration to the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> he let them know, how he intended to have distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted his Fathers wealth among them; and how ANTONIVS did unjustly detain it from them both. Certainly there is not any thing prevaileth sooner with the ignoble men, than hope of gaine. No
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4203:21"/> sooner had he finished his speeches, and given away that to them which hee thought impossible to get for himselfe; but all was in a tumult. None was so sparing of his words, but hee had some curse in store for ANTONIVS: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one vowing the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of that man; whom they supposed to deprive them of AVGV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STVS Donative.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4203:21"/>
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>IN this hurly burly AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THONY quits the Towne, and is by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall voyce of both hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, declared an enemy to the State. An army is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to HIRCIVS &amp; PAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SA then <hi>Consuls:</hi> AVGV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STVS aged but xviij. yeres, being proclaimed <hi>Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and made head of the League against the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon foe. AVGVSTVS, as he loved not to bee absent from a necessary warre;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4203:22"/> so hee alwayes used to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve himselfe from the dangers of it: and therfore he committed the whole enterprize unto the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suls. Well knowing, that though the Officers and soldiers took most paines to get the Victory; yet would the honor of it be referred to him, as <hi>Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</hi> Whereas, if any thing fell out to the Army, not well; his beeing a <hi>Non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> in the busines, would bring his honor off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out staine. The <hi>Consuls</hi> therefore proceed in the warre against <hi>Anthony:</hi> who seeing little possibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4203:22"/> of prevailing, resolved to sell the losse of his own liberty, and his soldiers lives at a deare rate. And indeed the fortune of the day was so equally shared, that as the <hi>Consuls</hi> might boast of the vanquishment of ANTONY; So ANTONY might triumph in the death of the <hi>Consuls.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>AVGVSTVS now had as much as he could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, more, than hee expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; a populous Army
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4203:23"/> at his service. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore applyes himselfe so to them, that giving that among them which he had in present, and promising them greater favours, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as his fortune and their valour should ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance him: he bound thē unto him in an eternall bond of allegiance; and made them the first step by which he ascended the <hi>Royalty.</hi> The <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hearing of the young mans fortune, thought it best to strangle these hopes even in their Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles: and to that end, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree the honour of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4203:23"/> ANTONY, not to belong unto AVGV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STVS, but to D. BRVTVS; for whose defence (being besieged by ANTONY in <hi>Mutina</hi>) their Army had bin levied. Nor did they thinke this frost of unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected unkinknesse, suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to nip the blossome of his hopes: but they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed him the <hi>Consulship.</hi> These harsh proceedings compelled AVGVSTVS, his honour now lying at the stake, to enter <hi>Rome</hi> as <hi>Conquerour;</hi> and force the <hi>Fathers</hi> to grant him his desires. Having thus gotten what for the time
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4203:24"/> he aymed at, he generally shewed himselfe gratefull to all, and particularly to some of the Souldiers: paying them what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind by promise; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly protesting that without their ayde hee durst not have adventured into the <hi>Capitoll.</hi> So by keeping his day with the <hi>Military men;</hi> and shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Noble and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Nature, in a thankfull Commemoration of their service, hee added stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bonds to such as were already his owne; and won many dayly to his side, which before were
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4203:24"/> eyther <hi>Neutrall,</hi> or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>ANTONY in the meane time was not idle; but knowing that LEPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DVS was beyond the Mountaines with a puis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant Army, he posted thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and so farre prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Soldiers, that he was admitted into the Campe; where the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> entertained him with all expressions of love and welcome. AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TONY
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4203:25"/> perceiving the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile nature of <hi>Lepidus,</hi> soone perswaded him to leade his forces into <hi>Italy:</hi> promising him no lesse than the Lordship of the world, if he durst but shew his face to the <hi>Romans. Augustus</hi> having continual newes of this combinatiō, and fearing much the prowesse of <hi>Antony,</hi> now strengthened; conceived no cause so fitting and convenient to his ends, as to joyne friendship, and to enter into confederacy with them. (<hi>A.V. C.</hi> 710.) And this he did, not for any good will to eyther,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4203:25"/> but because being desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of meanes to resist them, and also to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the death of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther IVLIVS, which hee much laboured; he might with their forces oppresse CASSIVS and M. BRVTVS and after as occasion fell out, deale with them bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing severed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p>THis League was so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly cōfirmed by a bloudy <hi>Proscription,</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly following. Wherin to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4203:26"/> be revenged on their <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> they betrayed their <hi>friends.</hi> A lamentable and ruthfull time, good and bad, rich and poore, being alike subject to the slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Now was the time of IVLIVS CAESARS Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, thought to be the golden age: and every one began to curse BRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVS and CASSIVS as the Authors of these present miseries: whom they but lately honoured as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storers of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi> Nay the very <hi>Kings</hi> were deemed tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; and such as lived in their dayes, happy. The
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4203:26"/> poore <hi>Romans</hi> had not changed the <hi>Tyranny,</hi> but the <hi>Tyrants.</hi> Yea they had three for one into the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Such is the quality of us men; we know not our owne happinesse in the <hi>fruition,</hi> but the <hi>wvnt.</hi> Two of these <hi>Triumviri</hi> glutted themselves with bloud, taking pride in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the lamentable cryes and groanes of the <hi>people.</hi> AVGVSTVS on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary shewed himselfe much grieved at this bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous cruelty: so that his consent seemed rather forced than voluntary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:4203:27"/>
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Proscription</hi> in it selfe, though cruell &amp; tyrannicall, yet produced some good and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble effects in the <hi>Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke.</hi> For when by this <hi>Proscriptioa</hi> and the insu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Civill warre, the stou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test of the <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> were made away; few beeing left which durst endeavor to recover the old <hi>Liberty:</hi> AVGV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STVS did the more easily establish his <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4203:27"/> restore peace to the City. Moreover the prosecutiō of this cruelty so incensed the people against <hi>Anthony</hi> and <hi>Lepidus,</hi> that <hi>Augustus,</hi> whom most held excusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, found them alwayes his fast friends; if not for love to him, yet in spight to them. I cannot here o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the like effect sprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging frō the like cause, in our <hi>Rich.</hi> 3. Who (though far enough frō conceiving any such happy event) made riddance of so many in the then factious <hi>fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies:</hi> that leaving a Male in the one, and a female in the other, surviving;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4203:28"/> this <hi>Kingdome</hi> by a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage betweene them grew well setled, which might otherwise have beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine indangered by some new competitors. So un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>searchable are the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of GOD, and his wayes past finding out. But to proceed. <hi>Antony</hi> &amp; <hi>Augustus</hi> leaving the guard of the City to <hi>Lepidus,</hi> and with joynt forces march against BRVTVS and CAS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIVS, both overthrowne by ANTONY: whom therefore did AVGVSTVS put upon that service, as well to diminish ANTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIES forces; as to keepe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4203:28"/> his owne, entire. As for himselfe, eyther he in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy suffered himselfe to be driven out of the field by BRVTVS, to make AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TONY more worke: or else indeed durst not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the battell. Such end had BRVTVS and CASSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VS: Two men, whom Fortune seemed to be in love with on the suddain, and did as suddainly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake them. BRVTVS the more accomplished man; CASSIVS the more expert soldier. (<hi>A.V.C.</hi> 711.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:4203:29"/>
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>I Passe over AVGVSTVS wars in <hi>Italy,</hi> ANTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIES in <hi>Asia:</hi> the discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents betweene them, and their reconciliation by the meanes of OCTAVIA, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster to the one, and Wife to the other <hi>Emperor.</hi> As also how joyning forces together to oppresse <hi>Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> then Lording it over the Sea, and proud with the conquest of <hi>Sicilia:</hi> they received him into the <hi>Confederacie,</hi> and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4203:29"/> the Island of <hi>Sardinia,</hi> to his other conquests. To recompence which kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>Sextus</hi> invited the two <hi>Generals</hi> aboord his <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall Galley:</hi> and after a bountifull entertainment, return'd them safe to their Campes. I scarce have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard so great an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight, among so many able Politicians. And much I marvell with my selfe, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what confidence <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus</hi> and <hi>Anthony,</hi> durst so far trust their persons to a reconciled Enemy: or on what reason <hi>Sextus</hi> having both of them in his power would let slip so slightly that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4203:30"/> advantage; greater than which was never offered to a discontented and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious person. This I am sure of, that he afterward repented it; and could have wished that hee had hearkened to the voyce of MENAS his old servant; who had perswaded him to make his best of that opportunity. The Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Arragon,</hi> of old enemies made new friends, had the like enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view at <hi>Savona:</hi> which that notable Historiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, and States-man GVICCIARDINE, descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth with much wonder
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4203:30"/> and Commendation. Yet in the like case, have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and as I thinke, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, condemned LEVVIS the 11. and CHARLES of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> the Archpoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians of those dayes: in that LEVVIS at <hi>Peronne,</hi> put himselfe into the hands of CHARLES his Enemy; who also after a short restraint, dismissed him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>THese solemne expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of amity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4203:31"/> the three <hi>Generals,</hi> being thus ended; and ANTONY gone for <hi>Egypt:</hi> AVGVSTVS then began to contrive his establishment in the <hi>State,</hi> though with the ruine of his <hi>Colleagues.</hi> Hee beginneth first with SEXTVS, having by gifts and promises drawne ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS unto his side; who by reason of his inwardnesse with his Master, knew most of his designes. By the directions of this ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS, and the assistance of LEPIDVS, he quickly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrew SEXTVS: who flying death in <hi>Europe,</hi> by the hand of AVGVSTVS:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:4203:31"/> found it in <hi>Asta,</hi> by the command of ANTONY. After this victory, AVGV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STVS eyther having or pretending a quarrell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst LEPIDVS; entreth into his Campe, seiseth his person, and depriving him of all honours, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth him to <hi>Rome.</hi> A man that halfe against his will, stumbling upon the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; had beyond a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny desert of his, enjoyed ten yeares continuance of Empire and prosperity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:4203:32"/>
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>AVGVSTVS durst not have beene so ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, if ANTONY had beene in <hi>Italy.</hi> He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore advisedly removed him out of his way, before he would attempt this action. It hath beene ever a chiefe <hi>Maxime</hi> in <hi>Court-policy,</hi> to remove that man out of the way, under pretence of some honourable charge: whom we intend eyther to cast from his present honours;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4203:32"/> or else to make lesse po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> For which cause did AVGVSTVS also perswade ANTONIES absence from the City; to bring him at the last into discredit, and contempt. His dotage on CLEOPATRA, could not but draw him into many inconveniences. Neyther could his neglecting the <hi>State,</hi> to Ryot with his <hi>Lemman;</hi> bee other than distastfull to the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>People.</hi> Next, he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Sister OCTAVIA, to leave her Husband AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TONIES house, yet pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately hee perswaded her
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4203:33"/> to live there still, &amp; bring up his children: that so the <hi>Romans</hi> seeing her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble demeanor and love to her Husband; might the more heartily detest him; who so ignobly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly had rejected her. to adde more fuell to this flame of hatred, he readeth ANTONIES will unto the people: in which many of the <hi>Roman</hi> Provinces were bequeathed to CLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OPATRAES children; and other things ordained to the common prejudice. ANTONY likewise prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red many Bils against <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus;</hi> as that he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4203:33"/>
                  <hi>Lepidus</hi> from the <hi>Triumvirate;</hi> that he had divided <hi>Italy,</hi> amongst his own soldiers only; that he had not restored the ships, borrowed to make warre against SEXTVS.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>THose discontents secō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with an ambitious hope of prevailing; made them both resolute to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all to the decision of a Battell. <hi>Antony</hi> had a fleet consisting of 500. Ships, high built, and trimmed up rather for a Triumph,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4203:34"/> than a fight. His Land for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces consisted of 10000. foot, and 12000. Horse. AVGVSTVS had the like number of Horsemen, 80000. foot, and 250. good <hi>Men of Warre,</hi> snug and close, built more for use than ostentation. The <hi>Rendesvous</hi> is <hi>Actium,</hi> a place seeming to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out for notable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes: Here being fought also in our fathers dayes, that famous battaile; wherein the <hi>Venetians</hi> gave the world to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that the <hi>Turkes</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by Sea, were not invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible. ANTONY was on
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4203:34"/> the Offensive side, and therefore much doubted whether it were better to give the Onset by Sea or by Land. CLEOPATRA whose words were <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> perswaded him to the Sea-fight: not that shee thought it more safe, but that if ANTONY lost the day, she might with more facility escape.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <p>TO this resolution, when most of the Captaines had for feare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4203:35"/> one of the old sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers thus bluntly gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd it. <q>What a mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable security art thou possessed withall, most noble Emperor? Where is that ancient fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight, wherewith thou hast formerly preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all disasters; and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the enemies devises on their owne heads? Consider with thy selfe Noble <hi>Generall,</hi> what uncertaine friends the <hi>Wind</hi> and <hi>Sunne</hi> are? To how fickle an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thou dost trust thy fortune. Let the <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> and <hi>Phoenicians</hi> old <hi>Mermaides,</hi> borne and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:4203:35"/> nurst up in the Sea, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this kind of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. But let us thy true <hi>Roman</hi> spirits, try our va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor on the firme land; &amp; there fight for thy <hi>Empire</hi> and our owne <hi>lives.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps thou dost mistrust our faith. Look here <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony</hi> (with that he opened his bosome) &amp; thou shalt see many an hon<seg rend="sup">bl</seg>. scar, got in thy service. Wee are now too old to learn new treasons. Alter thy resolution; &amp; to please a woman cast not away so many:</q> certenly, the powers of heavē whē they decree a mans destruction over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw those
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:4203:36"/> Counsels by which hee should escape it. ANTONY turneth a deafe eare to this Souldiers wholsome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: and borrowing frō CLEOPATRA two or three kisses, as if from the fountaine of her lips hee had derived all his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; without any more ceremony, prepareth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe unto the battaile.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <p>AVGVSTVS on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, seeing a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of a Sea-fight, was
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:4203:36"/> yet in this comforted; that his Vessels were more useful and better manned, though fewer than his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. That his men to him were faithfull, and by reason of their many Victories, in good heart. But from ANTONY there daily revolted some Kings and Captaines of note, to the great encouragement of the one side, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartning of the other. The whole charge of the warre hee committed to M. VIPSANVS AGRIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PA, who failing in no du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a good Captaine, tooke from his Galleyes
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:4203:37"/> whatsoever might be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments to the valiant, or shelter to the Coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; all that was comber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some to his owne men, or advantagious to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <p>THings thus ordered; and the battaile ready o joyne, AVGVSTVS CAE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAR standing where hee might see and bee seene of all, is sayd to make this or the like Oration. <q>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes and Companions
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:4203:37"/> in Armes, I suppose it needlesse, to hearten you, which never were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with feare; or bid you overcome w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> never yet knew what it was, not to vanquish. Conquest hath alwayes sate upon the edges of your swords, and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beene written in your fore-heads. Be not now backward to adde this one to your other try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs. When after the death of my father <hi>Iulius,</hi> of famous memory, I first dealt in matters of warre; I rather found, than made you good soldiers. And during
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:4203:38"/> this twelve yeares ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice under me, neyther have you beene wanting in the duty of faithfull followers; nor I (I hope) of a vigilant and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Leader. Sure I am, I expressed my selfe as farre as I could; and more I would, had I beene able. Let not the number not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the adverse Gallyes, any way af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright you. The huge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Bulkes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them unapt for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment: and the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude over-clogging &amp; hindring the others; may
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:4203:38"/> as much further our victory as theirs. They exceed us in multitudes of <hi>Men;</hi> wee them in number of <hi>Soldiers.</hi> The meaning of the word <hi>Pilot,</hi> is unknowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. And for their <hi>Mariners,</hi> the best of them are but <hi>Carters, Reapers,</hi> and <hi>Harvestmen,</hi> raked out of the field; the rest the excrement of common prisons: wherewith their Vessels are loaded, not manned. The <hi>Generall</hi> is indeed a fit <hi>Captaine,</hi> for such a selected company. It is the same ANTONIE
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:4203:39"/> whom you once drave out of the Field before <hi>Mutina.</hi> I perswade my selfe, that neyther hee dares thinke of recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or you of losing, your former glories. It is the same <hi>Antony</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing shamefully chased out of <hi>Parthia;</hi> onely in that he was not <hi>vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,</hi> proclaimed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe <hi>Victor.</hi> It is the same ANTONY, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to make <hi>Rome</hi> subject to the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> and to distribute the <hi>Provinces,</hi> purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with the bloud and treasure of our <hi>Ancestors;</hi>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:4203:39"/> amongst <hi>Iras,</hi> and her fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chamber-maides. Nay indeed, it is not <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony</hi> at all; but the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow onely of that sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, which now is hid in <hi>Cleopatra's</hi> Cabbin. Courage then brave men of Armes; Bee, as you have still beene, <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</hi> To speake more, were to deteine you frō Victory. Onely this, call to minde your ancient valour. Remember that I am CAESAR, you <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:4203:40"/>
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <p>THis speech animated the new Soldiers, and confirmed the old: So that with a generall accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, they give the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sault. Death, wounds, and blowes dished in divers fashions, and served in by severall men, were the best delicates prepared for these unwelcome visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. CLEOPATRA be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the battaile, and doubting the successe; through the thickest of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:4203:40"/> ANTHONIES fleet, made away with the 60. Gallyes appointed for her Guard. This disorder made the breach at which the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry entred. <hi>Antony</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her flight, left his squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron also: and being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into her Galley, hoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed sayle for <hi>Aegypt.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in playing the part of a cowardly Soldier; whilst each of his Soldiers exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the Office of a couragious <hi>Generall.</hi> For they so obstinately persi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted in the fight, that AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS was faine to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them mercy sooner than they would demand
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:4203:41"/> it; and divers time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would accept it. At last they all sware Allegeance unto him. (<hi>An. V. C.</hi> 723.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>XXIV.</head>
               <p>AVGVSTVS no loser of advantages, spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth into <hi>Egypt,</hi> which he reduceth into the forme of a <hi>Province;</hi> making the people pay for fine 20. Millions of gold. By re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving this money he so weakned them, that they had no ability to raise an
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:4203:41"/> after warre; and by distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting part of it among his soldiers, he confirmed them in obedience. As for ANTONY he seeing his fortunes desperate, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the honours lost in his life, by a noble and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick death. And <hi>Cleopatra</hi> ennded her life, also not long after; a woman more welfavored than faire; wel-spoken, rather than either. <hi>Antonies</hi> Courtiers had seene many Ladies more lovely, none more prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; men being cheyned to her by the eares, rather then the eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:4203:42"/>
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <p>I Willingly omit AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS entry into <hi>Rome;</hi> as also the state and Magnificence of his <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</hi> His victory he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed so justly, that none felt the fury of the warre, but such as were slaine in the <hi>Battaile.</hi> To assure himselfe of <hi>Antonies</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, was his first care: burning in the <hi>Common-Forum,</hi> the Coffers of ANTONIE, unopened; wherein all his Letters
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:4203:42"/> from his friends in <hi>Rome,</hi> had beene inclosed. Well knowing that as long as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thought themselves suspected adversaries, they would neuer shew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves true friends. To the <hi>Senators</hi> and <hi>Magistrates,</hi> he made sumptuous feasts. To the <hi>Common-people,</hi> hee exhibited magnificent and pleasing stage-playes: and with all varietie of pleasure banished from both, aswell sorrow for the old <hi>Proscription,</hi> as feare of a new.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:4203:43"/>
               <head>XXVI.</head>
               <p>THere were two men most deare unto him, and privy to his Counsels; MECENAS and AGRIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PA: which in the object of their love differed one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this; <hi>Mecenas</hi> was a lover of AVGVSTVS; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa</hi> of the <hi>Emperor. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenas</hi> was of the ranke of <hi>Knights,</hi> a man of good and bad parts equally cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded. When his busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse required care, vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant and circumspect; at
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:4203:43"/> leisure times, excessively vertuous. <hi>Agrippa</hi> was the first of his house, a man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like fit for Campe and Counsell; one neither carelesse of a good name, nor covetous of a great. For although hee onely was the man, which van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quished <hi>Sextus</hi> and <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> yet well skilled in the humours of Princes, he gave AVGVSTVS the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of all his Conquests; making the vertue; not the reward, the end of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. So by doing nobly, and speaking modestly of it, he was without envy, but not without glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:4203:44"/>
               <head>XXVII.</head>
               <p>WIth these two AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS withdrew into a private Closet, and then brake unto them in this sort. Hee made first unto thē a long discourse of the Civill warres. Then added, <q>That having by his owne fortune, and the valor of his soldiers, put an end to the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, he was unresolved what to doe; Whether to resigne the <hi>Empire,</hi> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:4203:44"/> it still in his owne owne hands. That in a businesse of such impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, he durst not relye altogether on his owne wisedome. That hee had made them his judges, as men that could speake soundly, and durst speake freely: That he knew thē to haue more care of his honour, than profit; but of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> more than both: That his Counsels, which course soever he tooke, would not bee by them eliminated. Hee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore intreated them to consider what was to be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:4203:45"/> done, and to give up their verdicts.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <p>AGRIPPA after a short silence thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. <q>I know thou canst not but marvell, O CAE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAR, that I, who under thine <hi>Empire,</hi> am sure to be beyond precedent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted; should perswade thee to live private. I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme more thy honor, than my profit; the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good, then my particular preferment.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:4203:45"/> And yet perhaps my Counsell shall be as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, if not applausible as the contrary. I know thee to be no way deligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with lyes &amp; flattery; and will therefore deale with thee freely and plainly. Thou hast indeed put a period to the <hi>Civill warres;</hi> but to what end, unlesse thou dost restore unto the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> the liberty for which the wars were raised? What benefit can the people reape frō thy <hi>Victory,</hi> if thou dost use it only as an instrumēt for their greater bōdage? Dost thou think that the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:4203:46"/>
                     <hi>Romans</hi> having so many hundred yeares maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their liberty; will now be willing to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe it? No CAESAR, no. Flatter not thy selfe with these hopes. <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the younger, and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torius,</hi> were quickly cut off when their ends were once knowne; and IV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVS thy Father of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Memory, did not long live, after his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons seemed to bring the <hi>Common-liberty</hi> in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard. And shall we think that there is no true <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> spirit surviving; No BRVTVS living, to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:4203:46"/> attempt the like against thee? Believe mee CAE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAR, believe me, it is far better not to meddle with the <hi>Empire</hi> at all; than to bee forced to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon it. But say, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence will so protect thee, that thou mayst out-live such pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices; &amp; shalt thou also not out-live thy glories? This present age per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance will not censure their actions, because it dares not. But Posterity free from all respects of love or hatred, cannot but call them into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion; and brand thy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:4203:47"/> with <hi>ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and perhaps <hi>Tyranny.</hi> If thy designes prosper, they will judge thee to have risen unjustly; if otherwise, to have falne deservedly. How much better then were it, now when thine honour is without blemish, and thy reputation unstai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; to resigne thy au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority? Inded when SEXTVS lorded it over the Sea, and ANTONY o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Aegypt;</hi> it might have been thought want of spirit, to have depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed thy selfe from the Government. But now
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:4203:47"/> to doe it, when thou art without <hi>Rivall,</hi> in thy <hi>Empire;</hi> now, when thou art sole <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> of the worlds forces; now when the <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Senate,</hi> lye prostrate at the feet of thy mercy; were to strike dumbe detraction, and to make the world ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire thy Temper. Thou art at this present the joy and comfort of the world; there is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to thee neyther wealth nor fame. Heere then fix thy foot. For go but one step beyond this <hi>Non ultra,</hi> and thou wilt run into a
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:4203:48"/> boundlesse Ocean of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils, which have no end, but the lend of thy life and reputation.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>XXIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>NOt so, excellent A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GRIPPA, replyed MECENAS. I never hard good <hi>Pilot</hi> finde fault with <hi>Sea-roome;</hi> or of more Vessels cast away in the <hi>Ocean,</hi> than in the Streights and narrow passages. Our <hi>Republicke</hi> is a Ship, fraught with divers Nations: Shee
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:4203:48"/> hath beene long tost on the Waves of <hi>Civill dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentions,</hi> long driven up and downe with the Wind of ambition: and there is now no place so fit for her safety, as the unlimited <hi>Ocean</hi> of one mans power. This <hi>Empire</hi> at first rising, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not to require a <hi>Monarch;</hi> but it is now grown too unweedly, to be without one. Take then upon thee, O CAE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAR; this Empire; or to say better, doe not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake it. I should never thus advise thee, did I conceive any possible
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:4203:49"/> inconveniences. The <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> doth allow thee a competent guard of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and faithfull soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; whō then shouldest thou feare? Nay ill may I prosper, if I see any cause of feare, were thy Guard cashiered. Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies thou hast none. For such as were, are either already slaine by thy va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, or made fast friends by thy bounty and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency. To omit <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Sertorius,</hi> I will a litle touch at thy Father <hi>Iulius.</hi> He too good a sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier to be a <hi>Statist,</hi> was too heady and violent in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:4203:49"/> establishing his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nor could he cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly temporize, and suffer the <hi>people</hi> insensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and by degrees, to drop into bondage; but oppressed thē all at once. Againe he committed a great <hi>Solecisme</hi> in <hi>State,</hi> when discharging his <hi>Guard,</hi> he sought to retain that <hi>Emp.</hi> by faire means, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> he had gottē by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. I know thee O <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar,</hi> to be of a more wary and cunning behaviour. Learn also to worke out thine owne safety, by POMPEYS misfortunes. Hee after the finishing
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:4203:50"/> of the <hi>Ponticke warre,</hi> at <hi>Brundusium,</hi> disbanded his Army: and thereby merited to bee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an honest and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man. Certainly; he shewed himselfe in the course of this action, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertuous than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate and politicke. For presently he began to be contemned, and by this improvident weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of himselfe, made an open passage to his owne ruine. I commend his modesty more than his braine; Neyther did hee himselfe on better considerations, approve
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:4203:50"/> his owne doings; and therefore hee resolved, had he beene Victor in <hi>Pharsalia,</hi> never to have committed the like O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versight. So is it, and so will fall out with thee, O CAESAR, if in this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thou propose him to be thy Patterne. It is not safe AGRIPPA saith, to take the <hi>Empire:</hi> lesse safe is it to refuse it. A setled &amp; innative vice it is in man, never to endure that any man above our owne rancke, should overtop us. <hi>Romes</hi> second founder <hi>Camil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus; Scipio,</hi> that scourge
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:4203:51"/> of <hi>Carthage,</hi> were disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; and <hi>M. Coriolanus</hi> ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished by our Ancestors: only because their worth had lifted them above the ordinary pitch of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Doe not thou hope to fare better than thy Predecessors. Heretofore perchance, thou mightest have sought the <hi>Empire,</hi> to satisfie thy <hi>ambition.</hi> The Empire must now be thy refuge and <hi>Asy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</hi> Credit me, the <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Senate,</hi> after so many yeares obedience, know not how to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne: neither canst thou, having so long beene a
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:4203:51"/>
                     <hi>Governor,</hi> learne <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> Truth is in matters of domesticall businesse, a man may stop and desist where he will. But in the getting of an <hi>Empire,</hi> there is no meane between the death of an <hi>Enemy,</hi> and the life of a <hi>Prince.</hi> Thou hast already gone too farre to retire. Now thou must resolve to be CAE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAR or nothing. To say more were superfluous. Thine owne discretion will suggest unto thee, better Arguments. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, I know that thou hast in thee too much <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> not to governe.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:4203:52"/>
               <head>XXX.</head>
               <p>AVGVSTVS, seemed to incline to this latter opinion; whether moved with MECENAS Oration, especially his instance in POMPEY; or that he was before resolved to follow that course, is uncertaine. Howsoever, seeming with great attention to observe their speeches, and gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their severall reasons and motives together, he made this Reply. <q>A most hard thing it is, for a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:4203:52"/> minde, to make a well-joyn'd answer. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided I am, and troubled between your two opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; loath to follow eyther, sithence in so doing I must offend one. Yet sithence there is a necessity of Resolution; I intend, though I like well of thine advice, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GRIPPA; to follow thine MECENAS. In doing which, I am but an instrument of the <hi>Destinies,</hi> to put their will in execution. Often have I heard my Father OCTAVIVS report, how <hi>Nigidius,</hi> famous for his
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:4203:53"/> skill in <hi>Iudiciary Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> told him once in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen <hi>Senate,</hi> That he had gotten an Emperor for the <hi>Romans.</hi> As also, how <hi>M. Cicero,</hi> so renowned for wit and eloquence, dreamed that he saw Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter place me on the top of the <hi>Capitoll,</hi> with a Whip in mine hand. Certainly, if the powers of Heaven promise me so great an <hi>Empire;</hi> I will not bee wanting to my selfe: but will adde by my <hi>wisdome,</hi> to their <hi>influence.</hi> To further my designes, I doe desire you; nay I conjure you
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:4203:53"/> both: that as you have been ever ready in your Counsels; so you would not now be backward, in any necessary assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</q> This said, they presently enter into a new conference, how to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage a businesse of this weight; what <hi>Senators</hi> to acquaint with their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; how to dispose of the <hi>Army,</hi> not yet cashie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; with what Plummet were best to sound the minds of the common people.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:4203:54"/>
               <head>XXXI.</head>
               <p>THis Consultation en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, AVGVSTVS con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his affability to the <hi>People,</hi> and respect to the <hi>Nobles.</hi> An opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he had to expresse him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to both. There was at that time a Famine, which shrewdly raged among the <hi>Commons.</hi> To the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer sort, hee distributed Corne, <hi>Gratis;</hi> to others, at a meane price. Riches and honours he communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to both sorts; the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:4203:54"/> better to wipe out of their memories, the ancient <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> Such parts of the <hi>Citty,</hi> as were destroyed by casualty of fire, ruined by length of time, or defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced during the <hi>Civill-warres;</hi> he re-edified. Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of <hi>Common-assemblies</hi> he repaired; Temples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrated to the Gods, hee spared no cost, to adorne and beautifie. And finally so freely diffused his bounty, that there was no part or member of the Citty, which had not some taste of it. Next, he dismissed his soldiers, assigning them Lands and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:4203:55"/> habitations in divers parts of <hi>Italy.</hi> That so the <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> might conceive his <hi>Resignation</hi> to be reall; and yet if need were, his forces might bee quickly reassembled. Nor were AGRIPPA and MECENAS wanting for their parts, to promote the cause: but carefully acquainted some of the <hi>Senate</hi> with it, who stood well affected to them; and cunningly prepared o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:4203:55"/>
               <head>XXXII.</head>
               <p>THe foundation thus layd, and the <hi>Senate</hi> sate, AVGVSTVS rose frō his seat, and spake to this or the like effect. <q>When I consider, with my selfe, the infinite extent of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; I protest I stand at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze: Marvailing how such, as heretofore have raysed combusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in State, durst un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the sole admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratiō of it. What Natiō
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:4203:56"/> in the world, hath not eyther begged their Peace at our Gates; or felt the fury of our wars at their owne? What Countries have not wee h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rried with fire and sword, making the rising and setting of the Sun, the bounds of our Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It must questionlesse proceed from an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weaning conceit in thē, of their owne abilities; who thought themselves so fit to undergoe that burden, which none but the immortall Gods can carry. Of my selfe I will not say much. Onely I
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:4203:56"/> am not inferiour to <hi>Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> nor it may be, to <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</hi> Yet have I found in my selfe, by late experience, how unable I was to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the affaires of State; even then when I had two <hi>Coadjutors.</hi> There is no <hi>Atlas</hi> of strength sufficient to beare up this <hi>Heaven:</hi> No <hi>Starre</hi> of influence sufficient to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate this <hi>Spheare;</hi> No one forme of vertue suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to actuate this <hi>matter.</hi> Neyther indeed is it fit, that the <hi>Republique</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> ought to be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, should depend only on the life and well-fare
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:4203:57"/> of one man. There never was, since the beginning of time, a City repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with greater store of worrhy and able men; eyther to consult or execute. Never was there seene so grave and discreet a <hi>Consistory.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so many of both sorts, so fit to governe. I have by your Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the valor of your soldiers, put an end to al homebred quarrels. I have beene your instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to reduce peace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and externall, to your City: and desire now no other Guerdon
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:4203:57"/> or recompence for any former services, than a quiet and a private life; free from all such dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and inconveniences, as are inseparably annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Principalitie.</hi> Now therefore, and may my action bee auspitious and fortunate to my Country, doe I resigne my authority: commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my selfe, and the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> into the hands of the <hi>Senate</hi> and <hi>people</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:4203:58"/>
               <head>XXXIII.</head>
               <p>THis Oration ended, there followed a soft and silent buzzing in the house. Some supposed this speech, not to have so much truth, as art and cunning, yet smothered their conceits, for feare of after-claps. Others were Creatures of his owne making, and they hoping to <hi>rise</hi> in the <hi>fall</hi> of theyr Country, would not heare of a Resignation. Some few of the wiser
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:4203:58"/> sort, thought it not expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, to put the Reines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into the hands of the <hi>Multitude.</hi> The rest out of a sluggish and phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matique Constitution, chose rather the present e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state with security; than to strive to recover the old, with danger. All ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with a joynt consent proclaime him sole <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror:</hi> and solemnely intreat him to save the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> otherwise running to inevitable ruine. He for a while, as vainely denyed to accept the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as they vainely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted to desire him. At
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:4203:59"/> last, wearied with the clamours of all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; and importance of some in particular; he by little and little yeelded to their requests, taking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the <hi>Empire</hi> for ten yeares, with this Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, that if before that time expired, hee could fully settle &amp; order the present State, hee would give up his charge. (<hi>An. V.C.</hi> 725.) This hee gave out, not with a purpose of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance. (For at the end of every <hi>Decennium</hi> hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed his lease of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment:) But that the people seeing a nigh pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibility
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:4203:59"/> of regaining their <hi>Liberties,</hi> might not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice against him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, had hee for tearme of life, received the supreame authoritie; hee had no doubt hastened his owne overthrow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>XXXIV.</head>
               <p>NOt the title of <hi>Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> but the Epithite, <hi>Perpetuall;</hi> was the destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of CAESAR; Yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so great respect was to be had in the choyce of the title. The name of <hi>King</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:4203:60"/> he refused, as beeing odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the <hi>Citizens.</hi> Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would he be called <hi>Romulus,</hi> though he much desired it; lest they should suppose that he did affect the <hi>Tyranny.</hi> When the people called him <hi>Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> he rent his Garments, desiring them to discharge him of a name so hated: and being once called Lord, <hi>(Dominus)</hi> hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad also that title by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Edict. <hi>Princeps Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> was the onely title he admitted. Well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the like glorious attributes were heaped on his Father IVLIVS, by
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:4203:60"/> them which least loved him; onely to this end, that growing more and more into hatred, hee might the sooner bee dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched. Nor was he ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that the <hi>Common-people</hi> led more by appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, than truth; dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernd names more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than executions: and that the onely course to make greatnesse stand firmely, was to receive extraordinary Iurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under a Title not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensive. The name also of AVGVSTVS, put upon him by the <hi>Senate,</hi> as if there had beene something in
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:4203:61"/> him more than mortall, he denyed not: as a title expressing more dignity and reverence, than au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>XXXV.</head>
               <p>VVhen first at the hands of the <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Senate,</hi> he had for 10. yeares received the Government; there was appointed unto him two <hi>Cohorts</hi> of <hi>Praetorian Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> for the guard of his person; to whō the <hi>Senate</hi> allowed the double wages
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:4203:61"/> of a <hi>Legionary</hi> souldier, to make them the more vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant and heedfull in their charge. Over these, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed two Prefects or Governors, (Captaines of the Guard wee may best tearme them.) To commit the charge to one onely, might breed danger; to more, confusiō. <hi>Agrippina,</hi> to settle <hi>Nero</hi> in the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> prevailed with <hi>Claudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> to muke <hi>Burrus,</hi> whom she had at her devotiōs, the sole Captain: and <hi>Nimphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> falne from his hopes of setting <hi>Galba</hi> besides the quishiō; desired the cōmād of the <hi>Gard</hi> as the next step
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:4203:62"/> to the Soveraignty. In choice of these Captaines, he observed two Rules. First, he ever chose them, <hi>Ex ordine Equestri,</hi> not <hi>Senatorio;</hi> lest that so high a dignity, joyned to so high a Birth, might startle their resolutions to some designes against his quiet. Secondly, he made choice of two such, which were of contrary humors, and somewhat at oddes: That so the ill intents of one (if they should har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour any) might be thwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and revealed by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and both in a noble emulation should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:4203:62"/> to be most forward in his service. The next course w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> he took for his owne security, was a law he made to curbe the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wills and attempts of the <hi>great ones.</hi> For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it had beene formerly unlawfull, to question a <hi>Bondman,</hi> in matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the life and death of his <hi>Lord:</hi> AVGVSTVS passed an Act, that all such <hi>Bondmen</hi> should bee first sold to him, or the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</hi> By meanes wherof he kept the <hi>Lords,</hi> before presuming on the secrecie of their <hi>Slaves;</hi> from all close and private
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:4203:63"/> Conspiracies against him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>XXXVI.</head>
               <p>HAving thus streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened his person, he assumed to himselfe the <hi>Imperiall, Censoriall,</hi> and <hi>Tribunitian</hi> authority to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Sacerdot all</hi> dignity. As <hi>Emperor</hi> and <hi>Generall</hi> of the men of Warre, hee could presse Soldiers, raise Taxes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime wars, make peace; yea and put to death the very best and stoutest of the <hi>Senators:</hi> as <hi>Censor,</hi> it
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:4203:63"/> was in his power, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme corrupt manners, inquire after mens carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, to take in and put out of the <hi>Senate,</hi> whom he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted; to place and displace the people from an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable tribe to a lesse hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Yet would he not be called <hi>Censor,</hi> as a name too inferiour: but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted the <hi>Prerogative.</hi> After the surrendry of MANVTIVS and his asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate; two men so unfit for that <hi>Magistracie,</hi> that they could object no crime to old or young, of which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves were not gilty. The
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:4203:64"/>
                  <hi>Tribunitian authority,</hi> ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled hinder any thing at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted against his liking: It preserved his person from all contumely and injury; Giving him leave to punish as an execrable person, yea and without any formality of law; whosoever had offended him eyther in word or deed. As for the <hi>Pontificiall Dignity,</hi> it made him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more reverenced, not more potent. Onely it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his title, the stile of <hi>Pontifex Maximus;</hi> or <hi>Chiefe Bishop;</hi> and made him of authority amongst the Priests, and in sacred
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:4203:64"/> matters, things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned <hi>Religion.</hi> The light of Reason taught him, that it was convenient for him, beeing a <hi>Prince,</hi> to have command on all his people. He had beene else but halfe a <hi>Monarch.</hi> Such as some Princes are with us, who quit their <hi>Clergy</hi> to be governed by a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne head.</hi> These severall Prerogatives annexed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, seemed not yet sufficient: and therefore he so cūningly dealt with the <hi>Senators</hi> that they gave him a generall Exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the <hi>Coactive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of the law. Which once
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:4203:65"/> effected, he seriously and totally bendeth his Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to settle the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <head>XXXVII.</head>
               <p>TO what <hi>Republique</hi> hee should conforme the <hi>Roman,</hi> was his next care. The forme descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by <hi>Plato,</hi> rather shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how a Citty ought to be, than how it may bee governed. <hi>Aristotle</hi> bred in the <hi>free State</hi> of <hi>Greece,</hi> was no friend to <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies:</hi> and therefore no fit
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:4203:65"/> Instructer. <hi>Solon</hi> afforded the <hi>people,</hi> too much au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, the <hi>Nobles,</hi> too little; the <hi>King,</hi> none. The old <hi>Carthaginian Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gislator</hi> attributed too much to <hi>Riches;</hi> too little to <hi>vertue.</hi> The <hi>Pensian</hi> Law-makers allotted to the <hi>King</hi> too much, and nothing to the <hi>Subiects, Zaleuchus</hi> was rather an Author of some particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Lawes, than the framer of a <hi>Republique: Phalaeus</hi> and <hi>Hippodamus</hi> was as unimitable as <hi>Plato. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedaemon</hi> onely, and her <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> were found fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test for his purpose. For
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:4203:66"/> LYCVRGVS a man of a deepe reach; and brought up under the most able <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians</hi> of all <hi>Crete,</hi> well understanding that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt forme of Rule was mutable, and by conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence pernicious: fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his <hi>Spartan Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;</hi> out of the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the three good formes: their imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons rejected. Reserving to the <hi>King,</hi> absolute Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty; to the <hi>Nobles,</hi> conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient authority; to the <hi>People</hi> entire <hi>Liberty;</hi> all in a just and equall proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. AVOVSTVS as hee neglected the peculiar
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:4203:66"/> Customes of that State, Community of Women, Equality of Possessions, and the like; So in the maine <hi>Platforme,</hi> hee was a diligent follower of his Constitutions. So mixing the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of one, with the <hi>Liberty</hi> of all; that both the Lords and people without feare of bondage or sedition, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed their hereditary freedome. The <hi>Consuls</hi> and <hi>Nobles</hi> of the Citty assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, as formerly they u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; Matters of <hi>State,</hi> they handled by themselves: <hi>Ambassadors</hi> of forreine Nations, they heard and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:4203:67"/> dispatched. The <hi>Commons</hi> assembled in the <hi>Comitia,</hi> to enact Lawes, and elect Magistrates; as in the <hi>free Common-wealth.</hi> Yet so that nothing was done without the consent and privity of the <hi>Prince;</hi> who for the most part, nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated the successive Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate: leaving the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of him to that <hi>people.</hi> So that the change, as hee contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, was not violent and at once, but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and by the silent ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of both the Estates: as seeming to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:4203:67"/> consist more in the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Magistrate,</hi> than of the <hi>Lawes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <head>XXXVIII.</head>
               <p>BVt to proceed particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly: the first care he tooke, was to confirme <hi>Religion</hi> in the same state he found it. I meane <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> as the <hi>Romans</hi> used the word, for those particular though idolatrous formes of <hi>Worship;</hi> which to their severall GODS had beene used among them. This, though hee might have
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:4203:68"/> changed, as the <hi>Pontifex Maximus,</hi> or chiefe Bishop of the <hi>Citty;</hi> yet very wisely he forbare it; It is not safe for Princes that are setled in a long descent of <hi>Government,</hi> to be too active in such changes; But it is dangerous to attempt it in a <hi>Greene State,</hi> and in an <hi>Empire</hi> not well quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; inured to bondage: Men are more sensible of the smallest mutations in the Church, than greater changes in the State, and rayse more frequent trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles about it. The <hi>Romans</hi> specially were exceeding tender in this point. The
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:4203:68"/> ancient <hi>Aediles</hi> formerly received it into their charge, that they permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no externall, eyther <hi>Gods</hi> or <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> to bee introduced into the City. And by AEMILIVS it was enacted for a Law, <hi>That none should offer sacrifice in any publike place, after a new and forraine fashion.</hi> Excellent therefore was the counsell that MECE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas gave him, when hee first undertooke the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</hi>
                  <q>That hee should follow constantly the <hi>Religion,</hi> which he found established, and compell others also to doe the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:4203:69"/> like: For forreigne and strange rites (sayth he) will offend the people, worke many inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient alterations in the State, yea and most like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will occasion many both seditions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracies:</q> Words which he spake not to the ayre, but to a Prince excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding apprehensive of the best advice; Nor did AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS ever shew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe more carefull in any one <hi>Arca</hi> of the Empire; than in this. That which MECENAS noted, we find true in these later Ages, in times more skilfull of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:4203:69"/> than the most quiet houre of AVGVSTVS Gouernment. No one thing more hath caused so frequent, and so generall <hi>Rebellions</hi> in the States of <hi>Christendome,</hi> than altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Nature; I cannot therefore but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it, as a pious <hi>Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> in a <hi>late mighty Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch.</hi> Better some few corruptions should be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in a Church, than that a change.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:4203:70"/>
               <head>XXXIX.</head>
               <p>REligion thus establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed; In the next place the wellfare of the whole <hi>Empire,</hi> consisted chiefly in reforming of the <hi>Citty;</hi> From which as from the heart, life was convayed to all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces: And in the <hi>Citty</hi> the corruption was most apparant, in the <hi>Senate.</hi> With them therefore he beginneth, well knowing that crimes in men of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent place end not in thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves:
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:4203:70"/> but by degrees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come diffused among their Clyents and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Now in the <hi>Senate</hi> were many and desertlesse men, who had been taken into the <hi>Consistorie</hi> during the Civill wars: as they could court the people, and humor such as were most potent. Of these he expelled none by his own power: but making a speech to them in the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> of the ancient order and present Confusion of the house; he first exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to looke backe on their former lives, and to judge of their owne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:4203:71"/> and merits, for so honourable a roome. Then he desired some of them to picke out such among them, as were in disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>factious,</hi> and in life <hi>faulty,</hi> but loath to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive so ill of their owne actions; Which they did accordingly. Yet as it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten happeneth, that <hi>the great Thiefe leadeth all the rest to the Gallowes;</hi> and as <hi>Commines</hi> observeth, that after the Battell of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thillery,</hi> Officies were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from many for flying away, and conferred on such as ran ten Miles
<pb n="333" facs="tcp:4203:71"/> beyond them: So re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained many in the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> neyther lesse vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, nor lesse violent; onely more potent to maintaine their doings, than some others whom they had removed. AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS therefore joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to him AGRIPPA, proceedeth to a new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view. And certainely, it much concerned him in the setling of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, that none should have a voyce in that famous Councell, but such as were of able judgments, honest repute,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:4203:72"/> and well affected to the the Prince. An enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise which hee esteemed so dangerous, that permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted entrance to no <hi>Senator</hi> till he were scarched; him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe wearing a <hi>Brigandine</hi> under his Gowne; and being enuironned with 10 of the most couragious &amp; best beloved of the whole company. Such as hee found in eyther kind inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusable, he discharged frō their attendance; electing such into their places, which were eyther enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for their wisedome, of noted moderation, and strong in their dependants.
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:4203:72"/> Yet so that greatnesse of <hi>Revenue,</hi> was esteemed nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a fit <hi>Patronage</hi> for any if they were offensive; nor a just cause to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge interest in the <hi>house.</hi> Those of them which were rich rather in the guifts of the minde, than fortune; he relieved with honourable Pensions: and finally he bestirred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe so resolutely, that all confessed that they had need of such a wise <hi>Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> to cure that dull <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption,</hi> whereinto the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> was falne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:4203:73"/>
               <head>XL.</head>
               <p>IN other things he sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome did proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them as of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe: But when that any of them had conspired his Ruine, he referred them to the Iudgement of their fellowes. And this hee did partly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve unto the Court, the ancient Prerogative; partly, not to be Iudge and party in his owne cause: but principally fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the example of his father IVLIVS, who coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:4203:73"/> a wretchlesse contempt of his adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, used when he was least suspected, under-hand and by publike Officers to worke their destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Many also of them, whom the <hi>Senate</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, he would freely pardon. Conceiving tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the questioning of mē of high calling, would produce as much terrour; though it argued not so much rigor as the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Yet if extremity of Law was used towards some few, it was to settle quietnesse in the whole; and as it were a particular
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:4203:74"/> blood-letting for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall health. Those who had followed the factions of BRVTVS and ANTHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NY, he forgave freely. And not so onely, but by manifesting his words by his deeds, and adding trust and honours to his pardons: he made his Chayre of State more set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and immoveable. So CAESAR by erecting the fallen and broken Images of POMPEY, made his owne statues stand more firmely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:4203:74"/>
               <head>XLI.</head>
               <p>BVt the chiefe Act by which he brideled the <hi>Nobles,</hi> was an Edict by him promulgated, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any of them, his leave not granted, to travell out of <hi>Italy.</hi> For well he knew that in an Empire unset<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and Provinces not quieted, the presence and authority of men of that ranke, might rayse greater troubles, than could be easily suppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. Examples he wanted
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:4203:75"/> not; that especially of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> who after the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of <hi>Pompey,</hi> stirred such a warre against <hi>Caesar</hi> in <hi>Affricke:</hi> that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bought Victory at a dearer rate. Yet not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to imprison them, he licensed them at their pleasure to visite <hi>Sicilia,</hi> and <hi>Gaul Narbonoyse:</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces close to the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of <hi>Italy,</hi> altogether unfurnished for warres; and indeed such, as by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the variety of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures in them used, were more likely to weaken their minds, than to arme their bodies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <pb n="339" facs="tcp:4203:75"/>
               <head>XLII.</head>
               <p>NOw to give the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate</hi> some sweet meat, to their sowre sawce; he as much honoured and reverenced the <hi>Order,</hi> as ever it was in the <hi>free-state:</hi> submitting himselfe to their Iudgements; and appearing of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, at most of theyr dayes of Session. Out of those he chose 15. altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble every halfe yere, to be of his privy Councell, but thē chāging thē for others
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:4203:76"/> that so all of them might participate that honour; and yet none of them bee acquainted with too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his secrets. At his entrance into the <hi>Senate,</hi> he used courteously to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the <hi>Lords;</hi> and so likewise at his departure. Hee knew full well that it was noted for great pride in his father IVLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VS, so much to sleight the <hi>Lords</hi> of that <hi>House,</hi> as he alwayes did: never ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to them any obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sance, no not then, when they came to tel him what honors were decreed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:4203:76"/>
               <head>XLIII.</head>
               <p>THis Reformation of the <hi>great Ones,</hi> soone made the <hi>lower sort</hi> more carefull; both to observe good order, and to learne obedience. Yet did not AVGVSTVS referre all to <hi>President;</hi> but some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to <hi>Precept.</hi> The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Knights</hi> he enforced to yeeld an account of their lives: an Ordinance full of health: Idlenesse being the root of all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate vices, and publike
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:4203:77"/> disorders. To the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> in their <hi>Comitia</hi> and other meetings, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribeth Lawes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as himselfe listed. The old authority of the <hi>Tribunes,</hi> dashed in the <hi>Dictatorship</hi> of SYLLA, he would not restore. He suffred them to intercede for the <hi>people,</hi> but not to preferre or hinder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Bill</hi> to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or the prejudice of the <hi>Third estate.</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this <hi>Curbe,</hi> the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sort</hi> would never quietly have suffered him to sit fast in the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle.</hi> For had the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:4203:77"/> had their <hi>Tribunes,</hi> and had the <hi>Tribunes</hi> had their ancient dignity and power, which they had usurped: there had beene little or no hope; of alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the forme of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So different are the ends of the <hi>Common-people,</hi> especially if nuzled in a factious Liberty; from the designes of soveraigne <hi>Princes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:4203:78"/>
               <head>XLIV.</head>
               <p>THe City thus refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the principall errors and defects of it; he againe exhibiteth unto them divers pleasures: As Shewes of Fencers, Stage-playes, Combates of wilde beasts, publique dancings, with variety of other delightfull specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. And this as well to breed in them a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of the change; as fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring lest their cogitations, for want of other objects,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:4203:78"/> would fixe themselves upon his actions, and the old <hi>freedome.</hi> Horse-races, Tilts, and Tornaments, he gladly cherished; but he permitted them only to the Inhabitants of <hi>Rome:</hi> That so that City being the Seat-Towne of his Empire, might be stored with good <hi>Horses,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Riders. Such of the <hi>Commons</hi> as were behind hand, he relieved: and when that any of them had made him Heyre to their goods; hee well knowing that no good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did appoint to his Heyre any <hi>Prince</hi> but a
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:4203:79"/>
                  <hi>Tyrant,</hi> presently restored to the Children of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased, the whole Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. An action truly worthy of AVGVSTVS; as true a <hi>Guardian</hi> of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes,</hi> as a Father of his <hi>Country.</hi> Such Princes as gape covetously after o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens possessions, sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome enjoy the benefit of their owne. The treasures of Kings are then greatest, not when their own Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers are full onely, but their subjects rich.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="part">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:4203:79"/>
               <head>XLV.</head>
               <p>YEt one thing more he seemed to leave unto the people, which they thought most pleasing; Liberty of speech. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in sometimes they were so licencious, that they spared not AGRIPPA himselfe, so potent with the Emperour. But hee good man, never u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the Princes favour to the prejudice of any, seemed not to marke their
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:4203:80"/> taunts and slanders: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with greater modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or wisedome, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor tell. Neyther did AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS scape their foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish <hi>Pasquils</hi> and infamous <hi>Libels.</hi> All which he win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at, knowing, that Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelies of that Nature, slighted &amp; cōtēned, soone vanish of themselves: but if repined and stormed at, they seeme to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged. A temper which he learnt of his Father IVLIVS, who was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect at it. And certainely it was a notable poynt of wisedome in both of them. It is the misery of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:4203:80"/> the best <hi>Princes,</hi> even when they doe well, to be ill spoken of. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many times such fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, are with more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy dissembled than ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, by the greatest <hi>Kings.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="part">
               <head>XLVI.</head>
               <p>AS for this Lavishnesse of the <hi>tongue,</hi> it is an humour that springeth for the most part, rather from a delight in prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, than any malice of the heart: and they which
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:4203:81"/> use it are more trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some than dangerous. IVLIVS feared not the <hi>fat men,</hi> but the <hi>leane</hi> and <hi>spare.</hi> And so AVGV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STVS thought, that not men liberall of speech, but silent, close, and sparing of their words, were most likely to rayse tumults. Moreover, as long as the <hi>Common-peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> reteined <hi>Liberty of speech,</hi> they were the lesse sencible of the losse of <hi>Liberty in State.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the dayes of DOMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIAN, when not onely they were prohibited to commune together, but
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:4203:81"/> even their secret sighes and teares were <hi>Registred;</hi> then began they to looke with a serious eye, backe on the old and <hi>Common Liberty: Neglect</hi> is the best remedy for this <hi>Talking veine.</hi> When the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour is spent, the <hi>People</hi> will cease on their owne accords: till then, no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces can compell them <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> taxeth <hi>Vitellius</hi> of great folly, for hoping by force to hinder the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall reports of <hi>Vespatians</hi> revolt; that being the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to increase, not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish the <hi>rumor.</hi> And as much he extolleth (I will
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:4203:82"/> not say how fitly the Reigne of <hi>Prince</hi> NERVA; wherein it was lawfull for the Subject to thinke what hee would, and speake what he thought.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="part">
               <head>XLVII.</head>
               <p>THese courses though he tooke to rectifie the Senate, and content the people, yet he stayed not here. There were too many of both sorts, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and unquiet spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, who stomacked his proceedings: and under
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:4203:82"/> the pretence of the <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Liberty,</hi> were apt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bold attempt, and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine alteration. These as he winked at for the present, so he imployed them as occasion served, in his forreine warres. Wherein he followed the example of his father IV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVS, who when his sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers had displeased him, in their <hi>Mutinies</hi> and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults; would lead them presently unto some des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and dangerous ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. So weakning both his <hi>foes,</hi> which lay next unto him, and punishing those <hi>Soldiers</hi> which had
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:4203:83"/> disobeyed him. For though AVGVSTVS had thrice shut the Temple of <hi>Ianus;</hi> and cherished peace, no Emperor more, of so large a Territory: Yet when he saw his times, and that mens minds were active, and their thoughts disquieted; he could find presently occasion for some new imployment. In this a <hi>body politique,</hi> may be compared most fitly, to the <hi>body Naturall.</hi> when we are full of bloud, and our spirits boyling, there is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Physicke</hi> better than <hi>Phlebotomie.</hi> But if a
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:4203:83"/> veyne▪ be broken in us, and we bleed inwardly; our estate commonly is dangerous, and almost in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureable. So <hi>Princes,</hi> when their people are tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous, and apt to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; or that their thoughts are working, and hearkening after acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; doe commonly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them in some ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice farre from home; that there they may both vent their <hi>Anger,</hi> and employ their <hi>Couraege.</hi> For let them stay at home, to confirme their practises, and grow at last into faction:
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:4203:84"/> the State will suffer in it; if it be not ruined. We cannot have a fairer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of this truth than the proceeding of the 5. HENRY, and of the times next following. Whose forreine warres kept us all quiet here at home; wasted those hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and consumed those fiery spirits: which afterwards, the warres being ended, inflamed the Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="part">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:4203:84"/>
               <head>XLVIII.</head>
               <p>THe Soldiers some of them he dispersed as before I sayd, all about <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly,</hi> in 32. Colonies: as well for the defence of the <hi>Country,</hi> as for their more speedy reassembly, if need should require. Abroad amongst the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,</hi> were maintained upon the common charge, 23. Legions with theyr aydes, besider 10000. of his Guard, and those which were appointed for
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:4203:85"/> the bridling and the safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Citty. As to all of them he shewed an excellent thankfulnesse, for their faithfull services: So in particular, to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GRIPPA, and to one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whose name the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories of that age have nor remembred. This lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had valiantly behaved himselfe at the battell of <hi>Actium:</hi> and being sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to appeare before the <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Senate</hi> in a matter which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his life, cryed to AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS for succour; who assigned him an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate. The poore fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:4203:85"/> not contented with this favour, baring his breast, and shewing him the markes of many wounds; These (quoth he) have I received, AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS, in thy service, never supplying my place by a Deputy. Which sayd, the <hi>Emperor</hi> descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Barre,</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Souldiers cause, and wonne it. Never did Soveraigne <hi>Prince,</hi> or any that command in <hi>Cheefe,</hi> lose any thing, by being bountifull of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors to theyr men of war. For this act quickly sprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:4203:86"/> it selfe over all the <hi>Provinces,</hi> did so indeere him to the military men; that they all thought their services well recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, in that his gracious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to that one man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="part">
               <head>XLIX.</head>
               <p>AND now were they so farre given over to him, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours conferred on A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GRIPPA, could not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease their love; well it might their admiration. AGRIPPA was of a meane
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:4203:86"/> and common <hi>Parentage,</hi> but supplying the defects of his <hi>Birth,</hi> with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of his <hi>minde;</hi> he became very potent with AVGVSTVS, who not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made him <hi>Consull,</hi> but his companion in the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunitian authority,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vost of the Citie.</hi> So many titles were now heaped on him, that MECENAS perswaded the <hi>Prince,</hi> to give him his Daughter IVLIA to wife; affirming it impossible for AGRIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PA to live safe, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how open new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures lye to the attempts of Malicious men; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:4203:87"/> he were ingraffed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the royall Stemme of the CAESARS. On which cause questionlesse, for the stronger establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his new honours; SEIANVS afterward at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, but not with like successe, the like march, with LIVIA, TIBERIVS Daughter in Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="part">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:4203:87"/>
               <head>L.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Senate, People,</hi> and <hi>Men of Warre,</hi> thus se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally reduced to a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocrity of power and content: The next labor is to alter the old, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablish a new govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Citty</hi> it selfe. To effect which, hee da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed all former Lawes, by which the Allyes and Confederates of the <hi>State,</hi> were made free <hi>Denizens</hi> of the Towne. That hee conceived to be a way, to
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:4203:88"/> draw the whole <hi>Empire</hi> into one <hi>City;</hi> and by the monstrous groweth and increase of this, to make poore the rest. Therefore this <hi>Priviledge</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated unto a few onely: partly that in the times of dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, the Citty might not so much feele the want of suste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and partly that so ancient an honour might not be disesteemed; but principally lest <hi>Rome</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenished with so huge a multitude of stirring and unruly spirits, should grow too headstrong to be governed in due order.
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:4203:88"/> The greatest and most po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Cities, as they are pronest unto <hi>faction</hi> and <hi>sedition;</hi> so is the danger greatest, both in it selfe, and the example, if they should revolt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="part">
               <head>LI.</head>
               <p>THis provident course notwithstāding, there were in <hi>Rome</hi> men more than enough; and among them not a few male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, and murmurers at the present state; such as contemned the <hi>Consuls,</hi>
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:4203:89"/> and hated the <hi>Prince.</hi> To keepe these in compasse, AVGVSTVS, it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for him to be still resident at <hi>Rome,</hi> and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to bee absent; constituted a <hi>Provost of the Citie,</hi> for the most part chosen out of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators:</hi> assigning him a strength of 6000. men, called <hi>Milites Vrbani,</hi> or the City Souldiers. To him he gave absolute and Royall authority, both in the <hi>Towne</hi> and Territory neare adjoyning, during his owne absence. To him were appeales brought frō the <hi>Magistrates:</hi> and finally
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:4203:89"/> to his <hi>Tribunal</hi> were refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, all causes of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, not in <hi>Rome</hi> onely; but the greatest part of <hi>Italy. Mesalla</hi> was the first <hi>Provost,</hi> but proofe being had of his insufficiency, the charge was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to AGRIPPA: who did not onely settle and confirme the <hi>City;</hi> but speedily freed <hi>Italy</hi> from <hi>Theeves,</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi> and stopped the courses of many other troublers of the State.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="part">
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:4203:90"/>
               <head>LII.</head>
               <p>IT is recorded that in the Civill warres of MARIVS and SYLLA, one PONTIVS VELESINVS of the MARIAN <hi>Faction,</hi> told his <hi>Generall,</hi> that he did well to scoure the Country; but <hi>Italy</hi> would never want Wolves, as long as <hi>Rome</hi> was so fit a <hi>Forrest,</hi> and so neare to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre unto. The like might have beene spoken to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GRIPPA; That he did well, to cleare the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:4203:90"/> Rodes</hi> and passages: but <hi>Italy</hi> would never want <hi>Theeves,</hi> whilst <hi>Rome</hi> was so good a place of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge.</hi> For though he did, as farre as humane indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry could extend, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a generall Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both within the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and without: yet ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could he remedy nor foresee all mischiefes. Still were there many and those great disorders, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the night sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; when as no eye, but that to which no darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is an obstacle, could discerne the Malefactors. For in the first <hi>Proscriptiō,</hi>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:4203:91"/> many men used to walke the Streets well weapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; pretending onely their owne safety. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it was to make their best advantage of such men, as they met eyther in unfrequented Lanes and passages; or travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as their occasions did direct them in the Night.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="part">
               <pb n="471" facs="tcp:4203:91"/>
               <head>LIII.</head>
               <p>TO represse therefore the foule insolencies of these <hi>Sword-men,</hi> AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS did ordaine a <hi>Watch</hi> consisting of 7000. <hi>Freemen:</hi> their <hi>Captaine</hi> beeing a <hi>Gentleman</hi> of ROME. In the day time, the Guard of the Towne was committed to the <hi>Provost</hi> and his <hi>Citie
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:4203:92"/> Soldiers:</hi> These <hi>Vigiles</hi> resting in their standing Campes. In the Night season, one part tooke their <hi>Stations</hi> in the most suspicious places of the <hi>City:</hi> another, in perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all motion traversed the Streets, the rest lying in the <hi>Corps du Guarde,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve their companions. By which meanes, he not onely remedied the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent disorders, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served the <hi>City</hi> from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of fire also; Yea and secured himselfe from all night tumults, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with them (though but small) more terror and
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:4203:92"/> affrightment; than greater Commotions in the day. Never till now were the <hi>Commnn people</hi> Masters of their owne, both lives and substance. And now was travell in the night, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s safe; though not so pleasant as at Noone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="part">
               <head>LIV.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Cittie</hi> thus setled, his next study is to keepe the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> in a liking of the Change. But little <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique</hi> needed to win their
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:4203:93"/> liking, who had long desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the present forme of <hi>Government:</hi> mistrusting the peoples Regiment, by reason of <hi>Noblemens</hi> factions, Covetousnesse of <hi>Magistrates;</hi> the <hi>Lawes</hi> affording no security, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing swayed hither and thither by ambition and corruption. These <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,</hi> when he first rid the <hi>Government,</hi> he thus divided. <hi>Asia, Africa, Numidia, Betica, Narbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nensis, Sicilia, Corfica, Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinia,</hi> all <hi>Greece, Crete, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus, Pontus,</hi> and <hi>Bythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> being quiet and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Provinces,</hi> of knowne
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:4203:93"/> and faithfull obedience; he assigned unto the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</hi> But the new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Regions, such as had not disgested their losse of liberty, with whō any rebellion or warre, was to be feared, he retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under his owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Such were <hi>Tarra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conensis, Lusitanica, Lug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunensis, Germany, Belgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, Aquitanica, Syria, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licia, Aegypt, Dalmatia, Mysia, Pannonia, &amp;c.</hi> This hee did as hee gave out, to sustaine the danger himselfe alone, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to the <hi>Senate,</hi> the sweete at theyr ease:
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:4203:94"/> but the truth was, to keep them without armes, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe alwayes strong and in a readinesse. Question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse the <hi>Caesarean Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> growing so strong; and perceiving the <hi>Consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> so weake: assumed to themselves the creating, and establishing the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Princes. Galba</hi> was made Emperour by the <hi>Spanish</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; <hi>Vitellius,</hi> by the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; Vespatian</hi> by the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> and <hi>Pannonian:</hi> The <hi>Consular Provinces</hi> never stirring, eyther to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their attempts, or to revenge them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="part">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:4203:94"/>
               <head>LV.</head>
               <p>THese <hi>Provinces,</hi> the better to manage the affaires of the <hi>Empire,</hi> he had peculiarly specified in his <hi>Register,</hi> what <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes</hi> they payed, what <hi>Presents</hi> they sent in, what <hi>Customes</hi> in them were le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyed. That booke also cōprehended, the wealth of the publike <hi>Treasury,</hi> and necessary charge issu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of it: What num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Citizens</hi> and <hi>Allies,</hi> there were in <hi>Armes;</hi>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:4203:95"/> What strength there was by <hi>Sea,</hi> with all other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances concerning the extent, strength, riches; and particulars of his <hi>Estate. William</hi> of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> did the like, at his first entrance into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> when he composed that <hi>Censuall Roll</hi> of all this Kingdome; which we call <hi>Doomes-day Booke,</hi> or the <hi>Roll of Winton:</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto which, <hi>Taxations</hi> were imposed, and <hi>Aydes</hi> exacted. The greatest <hi>Princes</hi> have not thought it a disparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be good Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands; to know the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:4203:95"/> of their Crownes; and have an eye to theyr <hi>Intrado.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="part">
               <head>LVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BRitaine</hi> was left out of this <hi>Bead-roll,</hi> eyther because from hence there neyther was much hope of profit, nor much feare of hurt: or else because, being more desirous to keepe than inlarge the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; he thought it most expedienr to confine it within the boūds appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Nature. <hi>Danubius,</hi>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:4203:96"/> on the North; Mount <hi>Atlas</hi> on the South; <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates,</hi> on the East; &amp; the maine <hi>Ocean</hi> on the West: did bound his <hi>Empire</hi> and defend it. Some <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> have their limits layd out by Nature: and those which have adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to extend them fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, have found it fatall. The <hi>Persians</hi> never did at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to stretch their <hi>Territory</hi> beyond <hi>Oxus,</hi> but they miscarried in the action. And what was that poore <hi>River,</hi> if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared unto the <hi>Ocean?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="part">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:4203:96"/>
               <head>LVII.</head>
               <p>MAny who loved <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or expected preferment by the <hi>Wars,</hi> incited him unto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest and plantation of these Countries. <q>Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that the barbarous people were naturally bad neighbors; &amp; though for the present not very strong nor well skill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in Armes; yet mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> weake Enemy in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gather great str<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> That he ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="170" facs="tcp:4203:97"/> the warre, for his Father <hi>Iulius</hi> sake, who first shewed that Iland to the <hi>Romans:</hi> that it yeelded both refuge and supply to the Malecontents of <hi>France,</hi> and enemies in <hi>Germany:</hi> That he would lose the benefit of a weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Country,</hi> stored with all manner of provision; and the command of a valiant Nation, borne as it were unto the warres. That it was an Apostacy from honor, to lye still and adde nothing to the conquest of his ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors: that he was in all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity bound as farre as
<pb n="471" facs="tcp:4203:97"/> in him was, to reduce to <hi>Civility,</hi> from <hi>Barbraisme</hi> so many proper and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="part">
               <head>LVIII.</head>
               <p>TO these motives <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus</hi> replyed, <q>That he had already refused to wage warre with the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian;</hi> a more dangerous neighbour, and far worse enimy than the <hi>Britaines:</hi> That he had w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sart ground enough, in his own <hi>dominions</hi> for many a large <hi>Plantation;</hi> when
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:4203:98"/> he saw it needfull; that he had constantly refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, though with great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility he might, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer any more of the <hi>barbarous Nations:</hi> That as in the <hi>Naturall body,</hi> a surfeit is more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thā fasting; So in the <hi>body Politique</hi> too much is more troublesome than a litle.</q> That the <hi>Roman Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> had already excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>Persian</hi> &amp; <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niā:</hi> &amp; to extēd it further, was the next way to make it totter and fall by its owne weight: <q>that he had learned in the <hi>Fable,</hi> not to lose the <hi>substance,</hi> by
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:4203:98"/> catching the <hi>shadow:</hi> That many puissant Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions lay in, and about <hi>Britany,</hi> against whom <hi>Garrisons</hi> must be kept; and he feared the <hi>Revenue</hi> would not quit the <hi>Cost.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="part">
               <head>LIX.</head>
               <p>FOr the assurance of the <hi>Provinces</hi> already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, he dispersed into them 23. <hi>Legions</hi> with their <hi>Aydes:</hi> whose pay onely, besides provision of Corne and Officers wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; amounted to five
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:4203:99"/> Millions and an halfe of our <hi>English</hi> pounds, and somewhat more, were so sodainly payd unto the <hi>Armies,</hi> that we read seldom in the Histories of that <hi>Empire,</hi> of any <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie</hi> amongst the <hi>Soldiers</hi> for want of pay. An hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse whereof these a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges have beene little guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For the amassing of his treasure, and defraying of this charge; AVGVSTVS made not use onely of his owne revenue. <hi>Warres</hi> which are undertaken, and <hi>Soldiers</hi> that are levied for the <hi>Common safety;</hi> ought in all reason to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained on the <hi>Common-purse.</hi>
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:4203:99"/> Grandour and secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of an <hi>Empire,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes in all respects, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much the people as the <hi>Prince.</hi> For which cause, he erected an <hi>Ezchequer</hi> in the <hi>Citsy,</hi> which was called <hi>Aerarium militare,</hi> or the <hi>Soldiers Treasurie,</hi> whereto the xx. part of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans estate, was brought; according to the true and perfect valuation. This was esteemed an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burden at the first, and indeed it was: but that the people felt the sweetnes &amp; effects of it, in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon safety. In that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, the interest was
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:4203:100"/> greater than the <hi>principall. Subiects</hi> that have a care ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the common peace or honour; will not r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pine at payments and taxations, though more thā ordinary. It is a poore conceit to thinke that <hi>Princes</hi> eyther are able or obliged, to maintaine the warres without assistance from their people: or that the treasures, which in these respects they give the <hi>King;</hi> they doe not give unto themselves. I may perhaps repute him for a cunning <hi>Sophister,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> never for a faithfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; which coynes
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:4203:100"/> distinctions betwixt the welfare of the <hi>King,</hi> and the weale of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="part">
               <head>LX.</head>
               <p>THese Legions he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed as occasion was, eyther to curbe the <hi>Natives,</hi> or secure the <hi>Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> The <hi>Roman Empire</hi> seldome had such perfect peace but that there were imployments alwaies for the <hi>Soldiers.</hi> If that they had in any place a short Cessation from the wars;
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:4203:101"/> yet they were not <hi>idle. Idlenesse</hi> doubtlesse is the greatest enimy to <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Discipline.</hi> Therefore he kept them at such times perpetually busied: ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in paving <hi>Bogges,</hi> or in dreaning <hi>Marishes.</hi> By meanes whereof, he made not onely many of the <hi>barbarous Countries,</hi> both fruitfull in themselves, and profitable to the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer:</hi> but thereby also he secured his owne affaires, and disarmed his enemies. For many times the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous people</hi> trusting to such advantages; were apt too often to rebell:
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:4203:101"/> and having got themselves within those <hi>Myres</hi> and <hi>Fastnesses,</hi> stood on theyr <hi>Guard;</hi> as in some fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable or defensible <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresse.</hi> The surest meanes to keepe a conquered people, from all occasion of revolting, is to lay waste their <hi>Wood-lands,</hi> and make all parts <hi>pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable.</hi> The opportunity of a safe retreat, makes not more <hi>Theeves,</hi> than <hi>Rebels.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="part">
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:4203:102"/>
               <head>LXI.</head>
               <p>THose whom he placed over his <hi>Provinces</hi> and <hi>Armies:</hi> hee neyther would remove under 3. yeares government; nor yet continue after five. A longer stay might teach them too much of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the people; and perhaps prompt them, to worke into the favour of the Natives, and the men of warre; and so at last to establish in themselves a <hi>Soveraignty. Caesars</hi> long
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:4203:102"/> stay in <hi>Gaul,</hi> (a second 5. yeares being added unto that, which was first al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him;) made him so potent with the <hi>people,</hi> and gracious with the <hi>Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers;</hi> that in the end hee brought the <hi>Romā Empire</hi> under his subjection. And on the other side, to take them from their charges, under 3. yeares conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, were to have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them home, before they were well learned in the <hi>Customes</hi> and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Provinces:</hi> so making them unable, to instruct their <hi>Successors.</hi> As for the men whom he
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:4203:103"/> imployed in those <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands;</hi> he called them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes out of the most valiant and upright, in <hi>Campe,</hi> and <hi>Senate.</hi> A <hi>Prince</hi> more willing and desirous not to imploy men likely to offend; than after the offence to punish and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stise them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="part">
               <head>LXII.</head>
               <p>BEsides his forces by Land, he also maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at Sea two <hi>invincible Armadoes.</hi> The one lay at Anchor neare <hi>Ravenna,</hi> in the up <hi>Sea,</hi> to awe and
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:4203:103"/> defend <hi>Dalmatia, Crete, Greece, Cyprus, Asia, &amp;c.</hi> The other at <hi>Misenum,</hi> in the lower <hi>Sea,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and keepe under <hi>France, Spaine, Africa, Aegypt, Syria, &amp;c.</hi> Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was this the onely use of two such puissant <hi>Fleets.</hi> But in all probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they were to clense the Sea of <hi>Pyrates;</hi> to have a care to the conducting of the <hi>Tributes</hi> &amp; <hi>Customes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Exchequer:</hi> and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved also for transporting <hi>Corne,</hi> and other neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary provisions, for the sustenance, and reliefe of the <hi>Citty.</hi> In the ensuing
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:4203:104"/>
                  <hi>Civill warres,</hi> these two Navies proved to bee of great importance: The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of them giving as great a blow to the one side, as a comfort to the other. The principall as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of <hi>Otho</hi> in the wars, was the immoveable fidelity of the <hi>Misenian</hi> Fleet: and the siding of th'other with <hi>Vespati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> brake the hearts of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellius</hi> best followers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="part">
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:4203:104"/>
               <head>LXIII.</head>
               <p>AVGVSTVS as hee strengthened the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> in generall, so did he cast an especiall eye on 3. particulars: viz. <hi>Italy, France,</hi> and <hi>Aegypt. Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> rounded <hi>Rome</hi> the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis</hi> of the <hi>Empire;</hi> and therefore he ought to be well assured, of its good faith and allegiance to him. Nor was he igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that the <hi>Bellum Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale</hi> raised by the people of that <hi>Country</hi> in the <hi>free-State,</hi>
                  <pb n="198" facs="tcp:4203:105"/> more shooke and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered the <hi>Empire;</hi> than the Invasions of <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> or <hi>Anniball.</hi> Therefore as formerly he planted in it 32. <hi>Colonies,</hi> of old and trusty soldiers, to keepe it sure unto himselfe: So now he did divide it into eleven Regions; each ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving peculiar <hi>Magistrates,</hi> and under <hi>Officers.</hi> This not so much to ease the <hi>Citty Praetor,</hi> although hee had imployment enough at <hi>Rome:</hi> but because it was thicke set and as it were overlayd with <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> whose rising might endanger the <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
                  <pb n="199" facs="tcp:4203:105"/> So by his <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> he kept a Garrison upon them as it were, that they could not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt:</hi> and by his <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> and <hi>Iusticiers</hi> (as I may call them) he set so strait a Watch about them; that they durst not <hi>practise.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="part">
               <head>LXIV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRaunce,</hi> then called <hi>Gaul,</hi> was both a large and fertile Country: sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a people, valiant in all attempts, and in
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:4203:106"/> many desperate. A people with which the old <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> fought rather to maintaine their owne liberty, than to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. A people whose <hi>Progenitors</hi> had sacked the <hi>Citie;</hi> and finally with whom the <hi>Romans</hi> durst not make warre, till they had almost all the residue of the world in subjection. Remembrance of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Reputation, and store of money might oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion many desperate practises against the quiet of the <hi>Empire.</hi> The readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:4203:106"/> way to keepe them in <hi>Obedience,</hi> was to keepe them poore, for without wealth, high <hi>Stomacks</hi> may well <hi>feed</hi> on the hope of <hi>Liberty,</hi> but disgest it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. <hi>Licinius</hi> his <hi>freed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> was the fittest fellow for such an Office: who is presently made the <hi>Taske-master</hi> of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> used to pay a Monthly Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, which he much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunced (besides private and petty meanes of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing) by making foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Moneths in a yeare. The <hi>French</hi> Solicitors at <hi>Rome</hi> make complaint to
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:4203:107"/> AVGVSTVS. He sometimes yeilded unto them, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times excused his <hi>Freed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> some things hee would not know, many he would not believe; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers he dissembled. LI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CINIVS to make up his peace, sent to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour all his <hi>treasure,</hi> and that huge Masse of gold and silver by those unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes, heaped up together: which hee not onely willingly received, but his turne being served and the <hi>French</hi> not a little impoverished; he recalled <hi>Licinius,</hi> and sent <hi>Tiberius</hi> to settle the <hi>Province.</hi> So
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:4203:107"/> old and common a thing it is with great <hi>Princes,</hi> to suffer their <hi>Vice-Roys,</hi> and <hi>Vnder-Officers,</hi> to sucke like <hi>Spunges,</hi> the <hi>Wealth</hi> of the <hi>Subiect,</hi> till they are quite full; and then o <hi>squeeze</hi> them into their owne <hi>Coffers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="part">
               <head>LXV.</head>
               <p>BVt the <hi>Province</hi> whose tuition and defence he principally regarded, was <hi>Aegypt:</hi> not so much for the valour and animositie of the <hi>Inhabitants</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall strength &amp; scituatiō
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:4203:108"/> of the place. <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> having annexed it to his <hi>Empire,</hi> never committed the entire go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Iurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof to one man: fearing least he presuming on the wealth of the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and site of the <hi>Country,</hi> would settle the possession in himselfe. And so AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTVS calling to minde aswell the multitude, as the levity and incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie of the Natives; that it was very rich in coyne, and the <hi>Roman Granary,</hi> (as serving the Citty foure Moneths yearely with Corne) not
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:4203:108"/> onely trusted not the rule thereof into the hands of any of the <hi>Senators,</hi> but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly forbad any of that order, without his especial permission, to sojourne there. It is a principle in <hi>State,</hi> never to licence mē of great houses, and credit among the <hi>people,</hi> to have free accesse into that <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> whose revolt may en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>danger the whole <hi>Empire</hi> Wherefore it was a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse doubtlesse, in the Councell of K. <hi>Henry</hi> of that name the 6. to suffer <hi>Rich.</hi> D. of <hi>Yorke,</hi> to passe at pleasure into <hi>Ireland;</hi> where he had harbour and
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:4203:109"/> reliefe, and whence hee brought supply both of <hi>men</hi> and <hi>money.</hi> But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Aegypt, Germanicus</hi> entring once into <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> onely to see the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities</hi> of it, and returne; stirred such suspicions &amp; distractions in the jealous head of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> that hee spared not sharpely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke him for it. <hi>Vespasian</hi> also being by the <hi>Syrian Legions</hi> chosen Emperor, first assured himselfe of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> as the key of the Sea and land, with a small power against a strōg host, easily defended. This place he resolved to make
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:4203:109"/> his <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> if his desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes succeeded not lucki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And to this place hee hastened, after the defeate of the <hi>Vitellian</hi> army: that so detaining the ordinary provision of victuals; hee might by famine compell the City of <hi>Rome</hi> to stand at his <hi>devotiō.</hi> The govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this <hi>Province</hi> was by <hi>Augustus</hi> alwaies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to some one of the <hi>Romane</hi> Gentry; as lesse able, by reason of his low fortunes, to worke against the <hi>Princes</hi> safety neyther would he allow his <hi>substi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute</hi> the glorious attributes of <hi>Lievtenant, Legatus,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:4203:110"/> Vice-Roy,</hi> or <hi>Propraetor. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> or <hi>President</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> was their highest <hi>Title:</hi> their being even in <hi>Titles</hi> no small motives to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="part">
               <head>LXVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AVgustus</hi> having by these meanes reduced both the <hi>Citty</hi> and <hi>Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> under his absolute cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: and being now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining in strength, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of a sodaine &amp; violent sicknesse; began to call his wits to Councel, how to dispose of the <hi>Estate</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:4203:110"/> his decease. <hi>Male-child</hi> he never had any. His Daughter <hi>Iulia</hi> a woman of immodest carriage, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made further use of her Fathers greatnesse, than that she satified her lusts with the grtater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solence. <hi>Marcellus</hi> his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters sonne, and <hi>Iulias</hi> hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was a young man of an ingenuous disposition; and seemingly capable of the fortunes which atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for him. Him being yet young, <hi>Augustus</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the <hi>Pontificiall</hi> dignity, and <hi>Aedileship;</hi> yet once upon his sicknes, he privately determined,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:4203:111"/> to choose a successor in the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his owne family: &amp; not to leave the Empire, unto <hi>Marcellus,</hi> whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> held unable to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> it; But to his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in armes, <hi>Agrippa,</hi> a man daunted neither with adverse, nor altered with prosperous fortunes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="part">
               <head>LXVII.</head>
               <p>This <hi>Marcellus</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards so stomacked, that hee beganne to grutch at <hi>Agrippas</hi> greatnes; and to beare a vigilant eye on his plots and actions. Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Agrippa</hi> unwilling to
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:4203:111"/> offend him, under whose future government hee was in all likelyhood to end the rest of his daies; with much adoe obteyned leave to retire unto <hi>Lesbos;</hi> that so his absence eyther might allay, or remove the displeasure, conceived against him by the young <hi>Prince.</hi> An action full of wisedome &amp; magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For though <hi>Augustus</hi> cheef end was, to discoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the popular depē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancies of his <hi>sonne,</hi> by the favours heaped upon his servant: Yet did <hi>Agrippa</hi> know, that a Favorite ought to have so much
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:4203:112"/> in him of the <hi>Persian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> as to worship the <hi>Rising Sunne,</hi> and that hee should resemble old <hi>Ianus</hi> with the two faces; with th'one looking on the <hi>King Regnant;</hi> with th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, on the <hi>Prince succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="part">
               <head>LXVIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArcellus</hi> being dead, <hi>Agrippa</hi> returning married his Widdow; and on her begat two sonnes, <hi>Caius</hi> and <hi>Lucius,</hi> whose actions afterward afforded such variety for censure,
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:4203:112"/> that there was wanting neither much reasō to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, nor little to reprove them. On these two, or at the least one of them, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus</hi> now growne aged, resolves to settle the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, and if they failed, upon such others, as by the liberty of the Lawes, he might <hi>adopt: Adoption;</hi> in the estimation of the <hi>Roman</hi> Lawes, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>an other nature.</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity whether it be <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall,</hi> or onely <hi>legall,</hi> is the best <hi>supporter</hi> of the <hi>Armes Imperiall,</hi> Such as both fortifies the Prince,
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:4203:113"/> and assures the subject. Yet this he did not without much reluctancy &amp; a great cōflict in his mind. <q>Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times his thoughts sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested to him, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed <hi>Successors</hi> draw to them all the attendance, and respect, from the <hi>Prince</hi> in <hi>possession:</hi> that they have alwaies a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring desire, to be actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly seated in the <hi>Throne:</hi> That they suppose the life of the present <hi>Prince,</hi> too tedious; not caring by what means it were shortned: That sometime it is pernicious, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the appointed Successor himselfe also.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="215" facs="tcp:4203:113"/>
               <p>On the other side, his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoughts prompted him to consider, <q>in what a miserable distraction he should leave the <hi>Empire;</hi> if sodaine death should take from him an ability to nominate his heyre: The feare conceived in the whole <hi>City,</hi> at his last sicknes: that <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> of <hi>Epirus,</hi> was of all hands condemned, for leaving his <hi>Kingdome</hi> to the shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest <hi>sword;</hi> That the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mō-wealth</hi> falne into dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentions, could not be set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againe without a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mētable war, &amp; a bloudy victory: That the people seeing
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:4203:114"/> him and <hi>childish,</hi> would not only contemne him, but perhaps, endeavor to recover the old <hi>liberty;</hi> though with the ruine of the <hi>State:</hi> That it was the custome of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> to desire the eternizing of their deaths, by the downfall of their <hi>Coūtries.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="part">
               <head>LXIX.</head>
               <p>HIs minde thus distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and perplexed, at last he brake, in this mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <q>Thou hast <hi>Octavian</hi> a Wolfe by the eares; which to hold still, or to
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:4203:114"/> let goe, is alike dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. Many inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences may ensue, if thou dost not declare thy <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor;</hi> More, if thou dost. The good of the <hi>Republique,</hi> consisteth in knowing the future <hi>Prince</hi> Thine owne welfare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth on the <hi>conceale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> The <hi>Common good</hi> is to be preferred before any <hi>private;</hi> Yet ought <hi>Charity to begin at home.</hi>
                  </q> No, <hi>Octavian</hi> no; As thou hast receiv'd, so shew thy selfe worthy of, the title of <hi>Pater Patriae.</hi>
                  <q>Yea, and perhaps this designation may secure thine owne
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:4203:115"/> Estate. For what will it profit the people, to contest with thee when they shall see a successor at hand, eyther of thine owne body, or thine own appointment, ready to take thy place, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge thy <hi>wrongs?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="part">
               <head>LXX.</head>
               <p>THus resolved, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopteth <hi>Caius</hi> and <hi>Lucius;</hi> desiring, though he made shew to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, they should be <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suls Elect,</hi> and called <hi>Princes of the Youth.</hi> Yet wisely fore-casting the
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:4203:115"/> dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers incident to himselfe, if they should make their abode in <hi>Rome;</hi> he sendeth them with honourable charge, into the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces abroad: as well to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise them in <hi>feates</hi> of <hi>Warre,</hi> as to take away all cause of faction in the Court, and sedition in the <hi>Citty.</hi> Which <hi>mystery</hi> of <hi>State</hi> as it was anciently practised by most <hi>Princes,</hi> so at this day by the <hi>Grand Seigneur:</hi> who alwayes sendeth his eldest sonne unto <hi>Amasia,</hi> as Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereof; from whence, till the death of his Father, he never retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</p>
               <pb n="220" facs="tcp:4203:116"/>
               <p>In these journeyes dyed the 2. young <hi>Princes,</hi> a mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap which <hi>Augustus</hi> bare Nobly: neither banishing <hi>griefe,</hi> with a <hi>Stoicall Apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy;</hi> nor spending the time in womanish lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. having performed due rights to the dead, he adopted his Wives sonne <hi>Tiberius:</hi> A man for the conveniency and ripenes of his age, not <hi>unfit,</hi> in <hi>feates</hi> of <hi>Armes</hi> not <hi>unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert;</hi> in humane learning not ignorant: but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all suspected to be cruelly given, and possessed with the hereditary pride of the <hi>Claudian</hi> family: A
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:4203:116"/> strong medley of vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and vicious qualities. <hi>Tiberius</hi> such was the will of his Father, to establish the succession, with more stayes than one, adopted <hi>Germanicus,</hi> his brother <hi>Drusus</hi> sonne; Then cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding over 8. Legions in <hi>Germany,</hi> which done, he speedeth to his charge in <hi>Illyricum:</hi> This man, <hi>Augustus</hi> appointed to be his heyre, as it was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, &amp; not improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility conjectured: neither in care to the State, nor in love to the party: but to win honour to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and to make the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:4203:117"/> people,</hi> againe wish for him; whē they should see that infinite dispro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in all royall and Kingly qualities, between the old and new <hi>Emperors.</hi> A fetch after imitated by <hi>Tiberius,</hi> in the adoption of <hi>Caius Caligula.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="part">
               <head>LXXI.</head>
               <p>THe last (though not the least) helpe of the <hi>Empires</hi> establishment; was the long life and reigne of our <hi>Augustus:</hi> as having ruled the State 16. yeares before, and 44. yeares after his confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the <hi>Soveraignty;</hi>
                  <pb n="223" facs="tcp:4203:117"/> by the <hi>Senate</hi> and <hi>people.</hi> All the young men in the <hi>City,</hi> were borne after the first <hi>Decennium,</hi> of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</hi> Most of the old men during the Civill wars. Few had seene what was the ancient <hi>forme</hi> of <hi>Government;</hi> in the free <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> Many did not desire it. For at the present, enjoying peace both at home &amp; abroad, &amp; hearing what sad &amp; tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call reports their fathers made of the former trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and <hi>proscriptions:</hi> they cōtented themselves with the new government; as more esteeming a secure
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:4203:118"/> and happy <hi>subiection,</hi> than a dangerous and factious <hi>liberty.</hi> By which long time of <hi>Empire,</hi> and the policies already recited, besides many others, which I can neither learne by <hi>Relations,</hi> nor gather by presumptions; did <hi>Augustus</hi> so firmely settle the <hi>Roman Monarchy:</hi> that it continued many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeares, immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able &amp; vnaltered; though all his immediate succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors were in a manner Monsters, incarnate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, and indeed any thing rather than men. <hi>Tiberius, Caius, Claudius, Nero, Galba
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:4203:118"/> Otho,</hi> and <hi>Vitellius,</hi> both by their owne <hi>Tyrannies,</hi> and their Bondmens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, would haue rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any <hi>Monarchy,</hi> not founded by <hi>Augustus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="part">
               <head>LXXII.</head>
               <p>TO speake concerning the domestical affaires of this <hi>Emperor,</hi> is beyond my <hi>Theme.</hi> As either how farre he suffered himselfe to bee ordered, by his Wife <hi>Livia,</hi> or whether hee used variety of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, not so much to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a disordinate appetite,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:4203:119"/> as by so many women to fish out the secret de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes of many men. Hee was too exact a States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to be perfect in <hi>Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery:</hi> and in all his wars, was prosperous by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune rather than by valor, or his <hi>Captaines</hi> valour, than his owne. The <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> which hee found weake and in <hi>Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bish;</hi> he left <hi>Adamantine,</hi> and invincible. In behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our he was affable, and gracious; in his discourse sentencious: to the good, of a most sweet dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to the lewd and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honest, harsh and unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant,
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:4203:119"/>
                  <hi>Friendship</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with few, and that slowly; but to them, whom hee once loved, constant and bountifull to the last. Finally such a one he was, of whom I will only say what I find spoken of <hi>Severus.</hi> It had beene an ineffable benefit to the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> if ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had never <hi>dyed,</hi> or never beene <hi>borne.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:4203:120"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb. 5. 1631.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>PErlegi hunc Tractatum cui titulus est <hi>(An Essay of the Meanes and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sailes)</hi> Vnâ cum Epistolâ Dedicatoriâ ad Thomam Levet. Ar. qui quidem liber continet folia <hi>64.</hi> in quibus nihil reperio, bonis moribus aut sanae Doctrinae contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, quo minus cum vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Imprimatur, modo intra septem Menses proxime se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes typis mandetur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>GVILIEL. HAYVVOOD;</hi> Epis. Lond. Cap. domest.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4203:120"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>